<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue or conference betweene Irenæus and Antimachus, about the rites and ceremonies of the Church of England: by Samuel Gardiner, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
            <author>Gardiner, Samuel, b. 1563 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102819</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838581</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838581</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177636</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177636)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1098:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue or conference betweene Irenæus and Antimachus, about the rites and ceremonies of the Church of England: by Samuel Gardiner, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                  <author>Gardiner, Samuel, b. 1563 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Braddock [and Valentine Simmes], for Thomas Bushell, and are to be sould at his house, in the Petty Cannons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Bradock pr[inted]. quires A-D, Simmes the rest"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ I² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the rites and ceremonies of the Church of England.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177636:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIALOGVE OR CONFERENCE BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Antimachus,</hi> about the rites and Ceremonies of the Church of England:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> SAMVEL GARDINER, <hi>Doctor of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6.</bibl>
               <p>O praye for the peace of Ieruſalem: they ſhall preſper that loue thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>Richard Braddock,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Buſhell,</hi> and are to be ſould at his houſe, in the <hi>Petty Cannons.</hi> 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177636:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177636:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, AND MOST REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, RICHARD, BY THE PROVIDENCE OF GOD, LORD Archbiſhop of Canterburie, Primate of all England, and Metrapolitane.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBEIT the arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> which is the Church of god, be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pitched within &amp; without, with the Doctrine of the trueth, and good and wholeſome diſcipline, and therefore is ſafe enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the waues of wicked doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ouerflowings of vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Lorde of hoaſtes that is with vs, and the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> that is our refuge, ſitting at the ſtearne and houlding it, and pronouncing this bleſſing vpon it, <hi>I will bee with you to the end of the worlde:</hi> yet is it ſubiect to the rage of manie waters, to ſirtes, ſandes, rockes, Pyrates, and to euill minded paſſengers, that will rather hinder, then helpe in a ſtorme or daunger. The laſt is not the leaſt, that this barke and pinneſſe is to feare. For as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſayth, <hi>Omnem inſcenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem vehere poteſt nauis praeter fugitiuum,</hi> this ſhippe may beare any paſſenger, better then a fugitiue. We diuide theſe into two
<pb facs="tcp:177636:3"/>flockes, as <hi>Labans</hi> ſheepe and goates were diuided into two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, whereof ſome were blacke, other ſome party coloured. Thoſe of the blacke guarde are heretiques, in doctrine: thoſe that are of ſundrie colours, and cannot agree among themſelues what they woulde haue, but builde with confuſion of language, with the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Babell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen, 11 Iudic, 12</note> and with the <hi>Ephraimites</hi> cannot pronounce <hi>Shib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boleth,</hi> are thoſe that in a ſingularitie of opinion, make a defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whome <hi>Auguſtine</hi> noting with his inkehorne, giueth them no milder name then <hi>Schiſmatiques.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Schiſmaticus es ſacrilega diſceſſione, haereticus ſacrilego dogmate.</hi> Thou art a ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique (ſaith he) in thy ſacrilegious ſeparation, and an heretique in thy ſacrilegious doctrin.<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſampleth the firſt ſorte to a lyon, and the ſecond to a Dragon, ſaying: <hi>Tunc leo fuit cùm apeitè ſaeuiebat, modo draco cum occulte inſidictur:</hi> Then he is a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when he openlie rageth, and a Dragon, when he priuilie lyeth in wayte. Of this had woorthy <hi>Epiphanius</hi> reſpect, when he ſuited euery ſingular hereſie to a ſeuerall ſerpent. A ſimilitude that fell fitly into his purpoſe: becauſe no aſpe, viper or venemous creature, ſcatter ſuch filthy vomit againſt vs, and faſten ſuch venemous teethe vpon vs, as ſchiſmatiques and heretiques. With the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent neighbourhood of theſe two, as with the malignaunt aſpecte of two vnluckie planets, hath the Church beene miſerably diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted a long time. The heretique, like <hi>Iudas,</hi> hath alwayes ledde a bande of ſouldiers after him, and the ſchiſmatique hath neuer beene without his diſciples and ſectaries. Of heretiques we haue had ſuch ſwarmes at all times, as if hell had emptied it ſelfe, and cleane degorged her ſtomacke, on the lappe of the Church: the ſun and the ayer, that is the cleare ſunne and light of the worde, hath beene darkened by the ſmoake of the pit.<note place="margin">Reuel. 9.</note> The blame whereof is to bee giuen to the peruerſeneſſe of mens minds, that loue darkeneſſe rather then light, and to grope with the Sodomites, for a wall at noone daye, who will bee blind with their eyes open, and will not with <hi>Eli ſee</hi> the lampe of God burning in the Temple. The number of theſe without number I ſhall not, if I might, goe about to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, and comprehende in this narrowe roome and compaſſe of an
<pb facs="tcp:177636:3"/>Epiſtle. They moſt of them were occupied about the perſon of Chriſt caſting their filthineſſe againſt his holyneſſe: either deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the eternall nature of the ſonne of god, or calling into queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the trueth of his incarnation, or elſe violating the vnitie of his perſon, or elſe compounding and confounding the diſtinction of his natures. In his diuinitie erred, very rankelie, theſe of auntienter tyme, <hi>Noetus, Praxeas, Hermogenes, Sabellius,</hi> with whome wee conſorte <hi>Berillus</hi> and <hi>Marcellus,</hi> knowne by the title and name of <hi>Patripaſſiani,</hi> or otherwiſe ſurnamed <hi>Vnionitae,</hi> becauſe they wold not acknowledge three perſons, but onely three voices in the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Trinitie. Hereupon <hi>Arius, Photinus, Artemon,</hi> affirmed that the ſonne had a beginning, and was not euerlaſting. Again, <hi>Euomius</hi> and <hi>Aetius</hi> conceiued the ſonne to bee vnlike his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: which ſtumbling blocke while <hi>Ebion, Baſilides, Cerinthus, Carpocrates, Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> are warie to auoyde, they take a greate fall, profeſſing the Son of God to bee but a meere man. Further, <hi>Cerdon, Martion, Manicheus Valentinus</hi> imagined him to bee but a cypher, fantaſie or vaine imagination, or to haue brought a body from heauen with him, and as <hi>Apelles</hi> ſayth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact and conglutinated of ſtarres, or a bodye without a ſoule, as <hi>Apollonatius</hi> fantaſyeth. Which ſtinking dunghill of rotten here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies is ſtirred and digged vpp new, by heretiques of this age, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that roguiſh opinion of <hi>Eutiches,</hi> who giue to Chriſt a dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied bodie. Now the Neſtorians treade as much awrie of the other ſide, giuing two perſons to our Sauioure Chriſt, teaching that the worde is preſent with Chriſt by asſiſtance. Thus is Chriſts coate, that was without ſeame, miſerablie mangled with their circuler queſtions: Neyther hath the myſterie of iniquitie thus ceaſed, but Sathan that cannot put off his nature, by his emiſſaries and factiue inſtrumentes, the Papiſtes, the incendiaries of theſe dayes, hath kindled hot coales of fire, in the Church, and hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch poyſon into the boſome of it, as it muſt be a greate deale of Triacle that muſt purge is. But wee ſhoulde diſcharge our ſelues of that well enough, if wee could be at amitie and vnitye with our ſelues, and woulde fight with our ioynte forces againſte
<pb facs="tcp:177636:4"/>
               <hi>Edom, Babylon, Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Aram,</hi> with <hi>Ioab</hi> and <hi>Abiſai,</hi> and not ſtrike our ſelues with our owne quilles, as the Baalites launced themſelues, with their owne kniues. If our kingdome were as ſtrong as the diuels, diuiſion woulde ſoone vnioynte, and diſſolue it. For if Sathan be diuided againſt Sathan, how can his kingdome ſtand, ſaith our Sauioure Chriſt? But this is the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buncle, botch, and byle of our eccleſiaſticall bodie, <hi>we diſſolue the brotherhood between Iudah and Iſraell:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach, 11.14</note> whereas <hi>frater</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>quaſi ferè alter,</hi> we are brethren in euill, diuided in <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſcattered in <hi>Iſraell, Eccleſiae titulo armantur qui contra eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am dimicant:</hi> they are vnder the banner of the Church, that fight againſt the Church. It is <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> obſeruation, that there is ingendred in euery thing, and proceedeth out of it, that which in tyme, if it be not looked too, will conſume the thing: as out of wood commeth a worme, out of a garmente a moathe, out of a greene hearbe a canker, by which the woodde is fretted, the garmente is hindered, the herbe periſheth. This hath too liuelie an application to the Church. For in <hi>Adams</hi> houſe was a wicked <hi>Caine,</hi> in the arke of <hi>Noah</hi> was an accurſed <hi>Cham,</hi> in the familie of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was a flowting <hi>Iſmaell,</hi> vnder the roofe of reuerend <hi>Eli,</hi> were two vngratious waggeſtringes his ſonnes, <hi>Ophni</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas:</hi> in <hi>Dauids</hi> courte, there was the rebell <hi>Abſalon:</hi> in the the ſchoole of Chriſt, was the traitour <hi>Iudas,</hi> in the companie of the Deacons was the crewe of the Nicolaitans. How the ſetled ſtate of our church hath beene diſquieted with home-borne croſſe biters, male contentes and wranglers, to whome it is good sporte and gameſome, the diſtraction of the churche of <hi>Corynthe,</hi> ſome cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelues <hi>Cephiſtes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor, 1.</note> ſome <hi>Paulines,</hi> otherſome <hi>Apolloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> ſtyling themſelues <hi>Browniſtes, Barowiſtes,</hi> of the fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the familie of loue, and taking manye ſuch odde titles to themſelues, I woulde wee coulde forget, as wee well remember. If the ſame moulde that now couereth ſome of the authors, and ring-leaders of theſe rowtes, might haue ouerwhelmed their factions, we woulde not haue ſo ſharpened our pennes againſt them. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are <hi>belluae multorum capitum,</hi> beaſtes with many
<pb facs="tcp:177636:4"/>heades, and they infect like a byle in a bodie, like a ſinke in a citye, and they are ſparkes that ſet the whole church on fire, wee maye not forbeare them. For they haue doone more hurte alreadie, then anie can diuine, and like they are to doo more, if their argumentes be not in time aunſwered with a ſurioynder, taken from the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſcabbarde, that may choke their liues, and put them to a <hi>non plus.</hi> For the open perſecutor, is not ſo nefarious as the prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous zelous profeſſor. Of which I muſt tel, what a holy father ſaith, <hi>Venit perſecutor, &amp; non fregit crura Chriſti: venit Donatus, &amp; dirupit eccleſiam chriſti, integrum corpus chriſti manet, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter manus perſecutorum. The perſecutor came, and did not breake the legges of Chriſt: but in came Donatus, and broake the Church of Chriſt; the body of Chriſt remayned whole, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the handes of his perſecutors.</hi> The due regarde hereof dealeth with vs, to praye inceſſauntlie for the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and to enſue it (all we may) with contention of ſides, intention of mindes, inuentions of arguments: wherein, when we haue doone our vttermoſte endeuoure, we ſhall neuer doo enough. For bee wee more watchfull then <hi>Argus,</hi> we ſhall ſtill find more to doe. And here I may not let paſſe the deſciplinarians of our dayes, who in ſuch nice diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between vs will not be tractable: for whoſe ſake onely I pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this treatiſe, in a loue vnfayned towardes them, as I deſire to liue, as reuerencing manye of their perſons, and honouring theyr religion, tendring theyr zeale, but wiſhing it were ſeaſoned with more knowledge. Heerein the Papiſtes and they are as <hi>Ionathans</hi> arrowes, beyonde and ſhort the marke. I woulde we were all of vs middlings in the Kinges high waye, without turning aſide to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of theſe bywayes, of the left hand, or the right. Theſe labours I preſent to your Graces good learning, and liking, to commend them to the preſſe, or vtterly ſuppreſſe them, as it pleaſeth your Lordſhippe. For to whome ſhoulde I giue them, rather then to the Father of our Church, that ſtand no doubt moſt Fatherly affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted towardes vs, and maynteineth the diuinity that is heere hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? I haue alſo twice taſted of the louing inclination of your nature:
<pb facs="tcp:177636:5"/>and therefore theſe paines, as the abilitye of the whole man, are conſecrated to your Grace. The Almightye god giue you to ſee manye dayes in honour, to the honour of his greate name, and to the enlargement of the Churches tranquillity, ſo many yeeres now (bleſſed be his Maieſty) continued among vs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces in all dutie, SAMVEL GARDINER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177636:5"/>
            <head>To the learned brethren of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, diſcontented with the gouernement of the Church of England, and to all of that ſide, <hi>Grace and peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Take god to witneſſe, whom I ſerue in my ſoule, that in all ſingleneſſe of mind, in a tender regard of the peace of the Church, and the welfare of you al, I haue addreſſed my ſelfe to this treatiſe: his great name in my deuotions being firſt inuocated, that it would pleaſe him to ſanctifie theſe ſtudies, and to giue me the tongue of the wiſe, and the pen of the ready writer, to put forth thinges in ſeaſon to the ſtrengthning of the weak, to the encouragement of the forward, to the inſtigation of the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the conuiction of the obſtinate. In the vnqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſurance whereof, I ſpeake now vnto you, (my certificate being the cheerfulneſſe he hath giuen me, all the while I was in hand with the following diſcourſe:) and am ſo zealous in the cauſe: the fire of his ſpirit, the worke of all good motions, kindling the coales of theſe meditations. So that I take vp the ſaying of the Poet:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſt deus in nohis agitante caleſcimus illo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ouidius.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And though I ſpeake but to your eare onelye, or rather to the ayer: yet my witneſſes are in heauen, with what affections I
<pb facs="tcp:177636:6"/>am trained to this treatiſe that will beare me record, my ſcope is to ſhew you: that the oddes betweene you and vs are not of that importance to deuide and ſunder you from vs: but that ſeeing graue and godly authority will not that we ſhould come to you, that you for order and godly authority ſake would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your ſelues to vs. That by our ioynt conformity we might all proceede in the common cauſe of Religion, and leade the people in the right way, of the knowledge of Chriſt crucified: as the Iſraelites ledde <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Hebron,</hi> with a ſimple and perfect heart. That thereby we might be built like <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that is a city that is at vnity with it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Ezech. 37.</note> and as the Angles of the mercy ſeate, that turnes face to face: and not thus to be tyed back to back, as <hi>Sampſons</hi> foxes that made nothing but ſpoile and waſte where they went: or to be as a diſordered or confuſed army of ſuch ſeuerall behauiour: one part ioyning, another deuiding companyes: Some ſtanding ſtill, other ſome running away. Read with Iudgement without preiudice, and let me haue but loue for loue again, and I deſire no more. And ſo much I do deſerue: wherefore if thou beeſt wanting therin, thou doeſt me more wrong, &amp; the blame is only thine. Reaſon would that none ſhould be ſo wedded to his will: but that he ſhould change it, when better reaſon mooueth. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:177636:6"/>
               <head>A Dialogue or conference, betweene <hi>Jrenaeus</hi> and <hi>Antimachus,</hi> about the rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>RENAEVS.</speaker>
                  <p>Well met my good friend <hi>Antimachus,</hi> how doe you, you looke ſomwhat ſadly, what is the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſad indeed, becauſe I may not vſe the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my conſcience, and becauſe for conſcience ſake onely, I am depriued of my liuing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed if it be ſo, you haue cauſe to be ſad. But I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile it ſhoulde bee ſo in this Realme of England, where the goſpell is freely preached by publique authority, and the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers thereof are ſo countenanced, by the king and ſtate. I feare you are not conformable to the diſcipline of the Church: and ſo haue offended the law in that caſe, for which you are ſo cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>True, this is the onelye argument of my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>And why may not you with a good conſcience, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the orders of the Church, as well as others, that are graue, and learned and are not to be touched with Popery, for order and peace ſake.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:177636:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue many reaſons whie indeede and in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience I can not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren:</speaker>
                  <p>I pray let vs heare them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus:</speaker>
                  <p>It is to no purpoſe to tell them you: for they will not mooue you: for you will be an abſolute formaliſt, when I haue ſaide what I can, and you can conceiue what they are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>Though I conceiue moſt of them, yet I would gladly heare them all, and conferre with you about them, and if your reaſons be better than mine, I ſhall promiſe you to turne coppy and to be of your mind, requiring the like condition at your hands, if in diſputation I ſhal vanquiſh you: And this is an equal courſe of both ſides, which no ſcholler ſhoulde refuſe, and wee haue both of vs been ſchollers in in our time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>I know enough in theſe matters already, and they are without diſputation or queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>I would not haue any that beareth the name of a ſcholler to ſay ſo. There is none ſo learned, but by reading and conference he may adde more to his learning. It was <hi>Solons</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, one of the Sages of Greece, <hi>ſeneſco ſemper multa addiſcens.</hi> And <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> the Emperour, only to learne ſomthing from his mouth, often went to viſit <hi>Sextius</hi> the philoſopher, at his houſe, ſaying: <hi>Pulchrum ſeneſcenti diſcere,</hi> It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable in an old man to learne. And <hi>Saluius Iulianus,</hi> a woorthy law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, was wont to ſay, though he had one foote in the graue, that he would ſtill learne. Yea, he that is moſt learned, may learn of another, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did of <hi>lethro.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I am content. Let vs then walke, and talke together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus</speaker>
                  <p>But will you then yeelde, if you haue the weaker ſide, and ſubſcribe to the orders of the Church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>I will. And you againe will reuerſe your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent mind, and concur in iudgement with me, if I ſnall perſwade my cauſe by better reaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Elſe it were no bargaine: I will with all my hart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>Then begin when you will.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:177636:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>But let vs begin with prayer, and ſo we ſhall ſpeed the better.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>It is well ſaid, I like that wel, conceiue you the prayer, and I ſhall ioyne with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Lord thou haſt giuen vs thy holy word, as a lantern to our feete, and a light vnto our pathes: illuminate our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thou that art the father of lights, with the light of thy ſpirit: and let the ſunne beames of thy holy word ſhine vpon our heartes: that the eye of our inward man may be opened, and we may ſee the trueth, and follow it in loue, and with one mind glorifie thy name, and ſeeke the peace and tranquillity of the Church, and the common ſaluation. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then <hi>Antimachus,</hi> that we may haue ſome ground to ſtand on, what are the points that you ſtand vpon, that you do miſlike?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>I differ chiefly from you in two points: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the garments of the miniſters, and eſpecially in the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſe: but moſt of all in the croſſe in baptiſme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Why in the garments?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, becauſe this diſtinction of garments that are enioyned vs, doe properly appertaine to the prieſthood of <hi>Aaron:</hi> which is now out of date, and is not to be reuerſed, anſwer me to that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>That is a knot eaſie to be vndone, and I thus aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer you. In the law and prieſthood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> there were ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by which it pleaſed God to conſigne his promiſes of Chriſt, that was to come, all which I acknowledge to be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and that we are to beleeue that Chriſt is giuen, and is not now to be giuen, and, other new ſignes and charters of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, in the roome of the old, being ordained vnder the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, by the Lord himſelf, which are bread and wine, we are not to bring into vſe againe, the old ſeales and markes. But yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, there were there ſome actions, that were of that nature, as they could not kindlie be called ſacraments, for they ſerued for decencie, and order, and ſome apt vſe, which as
<pb facs="tcp:177636:8"/>hauing good congruitie with the light of nature, and ſomwhat appertaining to our good, I am of the mind, that they may be reuiued and retayned; who doth not know, that the Apoſtles for the peace and fellowſhip of the faithfull, did giue in commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to the Church, that they ſhould abſtaine from thinges, offered to Idols, and from bloud, and that is ſtrangled: which queſtionleſſe, were prouiſoes in the law, belonging to the prieſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hood of <hi>Aaron,</hi> if we will generally reſpect what that law deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. Tythes alſo are in vſe, in moſt churches, which we ſhal not find mentioned in the new Teſtament, which we doubt not to be due by the law of god now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it being as free for any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an magiſtrate, to deduct ciuill lawes from the Iewiſh policie, as for the Romanes, to borrow from the Athenians, and ſome ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Germanie,</hi> from the <hi>Venetians,</hi> certaine of their ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Moſes</hi> was the captaine lawgiuer, with whome <hi>Theſeus, Romulus, Minos, Numa, Solon,</hi> are no way to be compared. We alſo giue inſtance of Pſalmes and Hymnes, which take not I ſuppoſe any authority from the lawe of the goſpell, but they haue very good foundation, in the old charter. Moreouer, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> expounding the fourteenth chapter and 26. verſe of the firſt epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> plainly ſayth, that the manner of prophecying, there deliuered by <hi>Paul,</hi> was borrowed from the ſynagogues, and brought into our churches. We haue alſo feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall dayes, in remembrance of the birth, death, reſurrection, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion of our Sauiour Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Shall we aboliſh all theſe, becauſe they haue ſo nigh neighbourhood, and cognation with the old legall, and leuiticall ceremonies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue here opened a gap, to manie ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as to holy water, perfumes, and infinite ſuch trinkets.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo, for we replie further, that there is a meane and moderation to be holden, in the entertaining of primatiue ceremonies, that the church be not aggrauated or ſurcharged, with theſe things: and that we are not to giue any religion vnto them, as there was to holy water, incenſe and ſuch things. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, we warne Chriſtians to be cautelous, that they endanger not their Chriſtian liberty, that albeit ſome antienter ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
<pb facs="tcp:177636:8"/>be reſtored, yet they be not ſo receiued, as neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. But ſo to tolerate and vſe them, as when it ſhall ſeeme good by higher powers, they may as ſuperfluous or little profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, grow out of vſe, as it may well be done in theſe garments, when it ſhall pleaſe our commaunders. In the meane while, let vs be contented, and imbrace the ſweet peace and welfare of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vs, vnder ſuch gentle fauourable, and honeſt conditions. The learned brethren in the daies of Queen <hi>Marie,</hi> would haue embraced with both armes, ſuch a conſideration as this for the purchaſe of their liues and liberty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>It is to purpoſe that you ſay, but I aſſault you with a new argument, thus. Theſe garments that are enioyned vs, are reliques of Rome, and old Popiſh traſh: wherfore, as we haue renounced the Pope and his religion, we ought to haue no thing to do with his reliques of ſuperſtition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall neuer prooue, that this different habite, of the miniſters, that you can not like, was firſt founded by the Pope. I am ſure that the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in the ſacrifices of <hi>Iſis</hi> long before euer there was a Pope, were cloathed with white gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the <hi>Poet Ouid</hi> teſtifieth, ſaying;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nunc dea linigera colitur celeberrima turba.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The goddeſſe great, by euerie wight,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ouidlus.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is now ador'd with garments white.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And we find in the ſtories of the Church, that <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle ware at <hi>Epheſus</hi> a pontificall breaſt plate. And the Deacon <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> witneſſeth of <hi>Cyprian</hi> the Martyr, that when he was to dye, he gaue his ſurpleſſe to the Deacons, and ſtood in linnen robes. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſheweth, that there was an vniforme habite of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in miniſtration and ſeruice of religion?<note place="margin">Hieron. li. 13. in 44. Ezech.</note> and a diftering at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire for the vſe of common life. This vniforme habite which was vſed in the religion of god, by the Biſhop, prieſt, and Deacon, was the white veſture as the ſame father elſewhere teacheth,<note place="margin">Hieron. li. 1. aduerſ. pelag. lib. 1. cap. 9.</note> ſaying: <hi>Is it any enmitie to god, if I weare a white garment, that is comelie? If the Biſhop, prieſt, or Deacon, and the reſt of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ranke, come to adminiſter the vſuall ſacrifice in a white ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, are they therefore hereby Gods aduerſaries?</hi> Now that it was
<pb facs="tcp:177636:9"/>the receiued vſe of thoſe times, wherein that holy father <hi>Hierom</hi> liued, to put on white garments, in the execution of diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and in the celebration of the bleſſed ſacraments, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Carthage maketh proofe, at which were preſent, two hundred and fourteen Biſhops, among whome was <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> The teſtimony of that Counſell is this <hi>Diaconus tempore oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis tantum vel lectionis alba induitur.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Concil. Carthage Canon 46.</note> 
                     <hi>The Deacon onelie in the time of oblation or reading, is cloathed in white raiment. Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> alſo maketh mention, of the white garments of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the church. Antient writers do report, that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans when they were conuerted to Chriſt, changed their habit, &amp; in ſtead of their gowne, tooke a cloake: for which when they were flowted by the heathens, <hi>Tertullian</hi> wrote a learned trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the cloake. And we may not be ignorant, that to ſuch as were entred the church by baptiſme, an <hi>Albe</hi> or white garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was deliuered. Wherefore hence it is a cleere caſe, that before the popes vſurped tyranny had beginning, there were no few differences of garments in the church. But to yeld you ſo much for further conference ſake, that the Pope was the Patrone of theſe garments: your conſequence will not hold, that therefore they are to be abſolutely refuſed. For to reſtrain vs from eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that the Pope vſeth, is to nip the neck of the Church with too ſtraight a yoake, and to lay too great a burden of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage vpon it. Truly our forefathers in a good diſcretion coulde appropriate the temples of Idols vnto religious vſes, and to the trew ſeruice and worſhip of god, and diuert ſuch reuenues as had bin formerly deuoted to vild vſes, as to the imaginary gods of the gentiles, to theatricall paſtimes, to their veſtall virgines: to the maintenance of Church miniſters. Wheras before they ſerued not only Antichriſt, but the diuell. The Poets did dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the fruits of their wits, their verſes, and pamphlets to their ſeueral Muſes and Gods, yet holy writers, where they haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any good ſtuffe, in them worthy of their vſe, they haue bin bold to make benefit of them, wherin they haue the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> their example, who brought three quotatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of poets, as of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nander, Aratus, Epimenides,</hi> into the body of the Bible. Who
<pb facs="tcp:177636:9"/>doth not alſo know that wine was conſecrated to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> bread to <hi>Ceres,</hi> water to <hi>Neptune,</hi> oyle to <hi>Minerua,</hi> learning to <hi>Mercurie,</hi> Muſick to the <hi>Muſes</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> and many other ſuch things yee may reade in <hi>Tertullian</hi> his treatiſe, <hi>De corona militis,</hi> where he dealeth with this ſubiect matter: all which we make no bones to vſe, as well in ſacred as prophane vſes, albeit they had bin dedicated to Idols or deuils?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue ſet a good die vpon a courſe cloath. This faſhion and forme of miniſters attire, is but an humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention: is it any more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>It is. For the linuen garment and veſtiments of the church, haue very nigh reſemblance of <hi>Aarons</hi> Ephod, and his other pontificall induments ordained by god. The linnen gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was after that a ſymbole of a profeſſor of religion,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. 2. Sam. 6.</note> as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muels</hi> linnen coate was to him, and as <hi>Dauids</hi> linnen Ephod was, wherwith he was girded when he danced before the Ark. And the roabes of our Biſhops are taken vp in immitation of the high prieſts robes, enioyned at the appointment of God by <hi>Moſes.</hi> But let it be an humane inuention, becauſe it pleaſeth you to think no better of it. Are you in that mind, that all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inuentions, are to be throwen out of the church? If you thinke ſo, then muſt we alter the time of our Communions, it being at ſupper, and firſt of all celebrated by Chriſt at night, and humane wiſedome hath lawfully enough diſpenſed with the time,<note place="margin">Act. 4.37.</note> and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated it to the morning. So that receiued order of the primitiue church, that the price of ſuch things, that were ſould, ſhould be laide at the Apoſtles feet, was meerly mans or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and conſtitution: wherefore you may aſwell ſtomack that, and except againſt it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>But I pray you what vſe is there of them, that you pleaſe to pleade ſo for them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly, much euery way. For they are not without good and proper ſignification. 1. For the linnen garment in diuine ſeruice is more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable then that which is of woole, becauſe it is a ſymbole and ſigne of innocencye and puritie: wherfore it is ſaid in the Reuelation, of the ſaints, that they ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:177636:10"/>be cloathed with long white robes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>Our ſacred profeſſion ſignifieth ſo much, let vs therfore ſample it, not ſignifie that purity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>You may tell <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much, when he decreed among the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Co. 11.5.</note> that the woman ſhould haue her head couered and the man ſhould be bareheaded, and ſtandeth only vpon the ſignification of it. You may herin ſay vnto him, let the man ſhew himſelfe his wiues head, and let the womans behauiour declare that ſhee is ſubiect to her huſband, and let them not by dum ſignes demonſtrate it. But the Apoſtles wiſedom thought it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofefull, that both by ſayings and ſignes they ſhould be leſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their duties.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there no other vſe of the garmentes but this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pithagor as</hi> giueth me this vſe beſide, that the lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen garment putteth me mind of my firſt eſtate, before ſin came into the world, that I ſhould labour what I might to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that againe: as the wollen weed doth ſet before mine eyes, the miſeries of this preſent life, of ſin, of death, the wages of ſin due vnto vs all, by the fall of <hi>Adam.</hi> For you cannot haue a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of wollen without the death or iniury offered to the beaſts that giue them, for which cauſe (as <hi>Pythagor as</hi> ſayth) wollen was an abhomination in a garment: but line and flax whereof the linnen garment is made, becauſe it groweth out of the earth without wrong done to the life of that is had.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>Can you yet make more meaning hereof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p n="3">3. Further the linnen garment is the marke of my high calling,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.1.</note> of the dignity of my place and perſon. For the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are called the Angels and meſſengers of the Lorde of hoaſts: and Angels almoſt alwayes appeared to men cloathed in white garments. Why ſhould we therfore come with ſuch ſhredding kniues, to pare the church of her lawfull liberty in the garments that it vſeth, and enioyneth, placing no religion therin, and being ſo ſpare of ceremonies as it is? <hi>Ierome</hi> in his ſecond booke againſt <hi>Iouinian,</hi> inhibiteth this white attire to Monkes, becauſe it was ſo triumphant and ſtately, as it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:177636:10"/>ſo in account among the very heathens. Wherfore their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates were called <hi>Candidati,</hi> becauſe they came into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of Rome, in white robes: Afterward, there were thoſe that were thus cloathed, that were called <hi>Candidati Caeſaris,</hi> who were <hi>Caeſars</hi> Secretaries, and read the Emperors letters openly in the Counſell houſe. In thoſe times none might weare ſuch a garment, but great men, ſuch as were called <hi>albae gallinae filij,</hi> men of great fortunes, and excelling in authority. Now then becauſe we haue obteined ſo high a name, as to be the Lords Angels, and Embaſſadors, let vs be thus apparelled like men of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. <hi>Achab</hi> and <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> went in royall robes. And religious Queen <hi>Eſter</hi> was apparrelled according to her eſtate.<note place="margin">2. Ring. 22. 2. Chr. 18. Eſth. 2, Eſth 8. Dan. 5. Act. 12.</note> And her good vncle <hi>Mordechai,</hi> was arrayed like an honourable man. So was <hi>Daniel,</hi> when he was aduanced, ſuite accordingly. So was <hi>Herod.</hi> A long gowne is fitting a counſellor, a ſhort veſture is for a day labourer or vulgar lay perſon, and the white orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath beſt correſpondency with the miniſters office, of ſuch dignity and preheminency.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>But in my mind the eyes of the people, that are wholy fixed vpon ſuch objects, draw away their minds from better thoughts. For as children delight more in the pictures, that are in their bookes, then in their leſſons: so the people, to feed their fancies, do more regard ſuch apparell, then the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of him that weareth it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>It will not be ſo if the outward ornaments of the church be but ſuch, as commonly haue bin vſed, eſpecially if they be plaine as the ſurpleſſe, rotchet, and the habite of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Biſhop is. For the vſe, and plainneſſe of them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and take away al manner of admiration. I would alſo think it more likely, that the people, whileſt in wonder they behould ſuch things, would ſall into further and deeper meditations of diuine matters.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>How happeneth it, ſeeing there is ſuch multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of good vſe in theſe garments, that many other reformed churches entertain them not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non eſt eadem ratio vrbis &amp; orbis.</hi> Lawes may dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:177636:11"/>according to the nature and condition of the place. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manners agree with other men, other meats delight other ſtomacks, other ayer is more fit for other natures, and ſo may other lawes be for other countries. But it is needefull that one ſtate ſhould be vnder one diſcipline.<note place="margin">lib. 10.</note> It is <hi>Curtius</hi> his ſaying, <hi>Eiuſdem iuris eſſe debent, qui ſub eodem rege victuriſunt.</hi> They ought to be vnder one law, that are vnder one Prince. For diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in lawes, maketh a diuiſion, and partition in the Kingdom. For as a painter, though he be neuer ſo cunning a workman, and ſhaddoweth his worke with neuer ſuch liuely and orient colours, to make two boords ſeem one; yet if thoſe boords be not better glued together, they will be ſeen to be two: ſo, that the church or common wealth may be one, the people muſt be coadunated or coanimated in one; or elſe a rupture in the frame of gouernment,<note place="margin">Delegib. lib. 6.</note> will very ſoone appeare. It is equality that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyneth friendſhip, and is the mother of friendſhip, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſayth. And inequality as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, is the foundation and ground of ſuſpition.<note place="margin">Polit. lib. 5 cap. 1. &amp; 2.</note> Now there is no equality in this, that ſome ſhould be ſquare, and others round: ſome white, ſome black. But hereof we will intreat more afterward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>But might we not haue an abſolute diſcipline and gouernement for the Church, though there were no can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons for apparell; but euery one were left to his owne choyce therin?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Though there were no Prouiſo in this caſe, yet rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould perſwade vs that we ſhould, as in other things, be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niforme in apparell. <hi>Gratian</hi> doth aduiſe vs to ſuite our ſelues in our habite, to thoſe among whome we do conuerſe: plainly ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he that doth otherwiſe, is eyther ſuperſtitious, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous. The gloſſary propoundeth vs this rule to obſerue, that in the forme of our apparell, we would apply our ſelues to the cuſtome of the place wherin we liue.<note place="margin">Aug. de doctr. Chriſtiana lib. 3.</note> To him conſent <hi>Panorun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus, Benedictus, Caprea, Baldus, Thomas Ierom,</hi> who commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Nepotian</hi> for obſeruing this rule. And it is <hi>Auguſtines</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in his volume of Chriſtian learning, that we diuide not our ſelues in theſe tranſitory things, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vnity of the church,
<pb facs="tcp:177636:11"/>and from the vſe of the times, and places where we liue. And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> holdeth it very decent, and becomming our duty, to accommodate our ſelues to the cuſtoms of the countries where we conuerſe, if we would not be offenſiue to any, or haue any offenſiue to vs. In old time at Rome, and afterward at Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, there were exerciſes and games of running kept, which continued to the time of <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour, where the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and curſitors diuided themſelues by their colours in their ſuites of apparel, ſome in green, ſome in a ſadder white. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon there grew partaking among the people, and chooſing of ſides, and therwithall ſuch enuy, emulations, affections, as after they had done their ſports, they began to be in earneſt, and each part to fight vnder his colours, that it coſt a deale of bloud in <hi>Aegypt, Syria, Greece. Ochoſias</hi> aſked his Legats, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had ſent to the god of <hi>Archaron</hi> for oracle,<note place="margin">2. King. 1.</note> of what forme and habite the man was, that met them: and they anſwered, he was a hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, and was girded about the reynes with a lether girdle. Which was a marke of knowledge enough to the king, though they knew not his name: It is <hi>Elias</hi> the Thiſbite ſayth he. So, as the Prophet was knowne by his habite, it were well that the Lords miniſters might be known by their formall attyre. It can not be deuiſed how we ſhould treade awrie, in framing our ſelues to forme of lawe herein, ſeeing no religion is repoſed in them, and that it is with other externe ceremonies, a mixt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of indifferrent &amp; middle nature, &amp; may <hi>adeſſevel abeſſe ſine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritu ſubiects.</hi> And as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth, <hi>Let no man iudge you of meate or drinke, or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the new moone, or of the ſabbaoth daies:</hi> ſo we may ſay, let no man iudge vs of apparell.<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> For as meat, ſo rayment, commendeth vs not to god. The ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition in this ceremonie is among the deſidious and reſty Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterers, the mopiſh monks, to whom it is great religion to bee buried in a Cowle, or monaſtichall habit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue ſaid in the matter of the garments, enough, and I hold them tollerable. But that which ſtabbeth my conſcience, is the croſſe in Baptiſme. And that is the hooke I can not ſwallow: 1. becauſe it is a dangerous addition to the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:177636:12"/>of the ſacrament: 2. there is no warrant in the worde of god for it: 3. and no one thing ſo much as that, hath bin ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly abuſed: 4. and there is no vſe of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>All your reaſons by your leaue are looſe, and we will prooue them ſo to be. 1. If your firſt ſuppoſall were true, you had ſaid enough. For the viall of the Lords curſe is powred vpon them,<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.</note> that ſhall adde, or withdraw from his booke, he ſhall be ſure to be blotted out of the booke of life, and to haue no part in the holy city. Be this formidable preſumption there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore far from euery Chriſtian: ſure we are, it concerneth not our church. For the inſtitution of baptiſme is performed by vs, as Chriſt commaunded, and no otherwiſe. The forme thereof is finiſhed, the ſacrament abſolued, and the child abſolutely Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianized, before it is ſigned.</p>
                  <p>Your ſecond argument, wherby you would conclude it to be vnlawfull, becauſe the word of God hath not warranted it, is not ſo warrantable. Our conſciences are ſatiſfied in this action, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the word ſtandeth not againſt vs. I doubt not that it is lawfull for the chiefe magiſtrate, to giue lawes and Canons for the church or ciuil ſtate, though they concur not ſo abſolutely with the word of god: ſo as they no way be repugnant vnto it. The Lord hath put the ſword into the magiſtrates hand, and there withall power to ordaine what decrees the thinketh good, in points of outward gouernment, ſo as they croſſe not or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front his royal lawes. <hi>Adoniah, Ioab, Agag</hi> and ſundry others in the old teſtament, were cut off by the ſword. But where find we this allowed, in the old lawe? For theſe ſtatutes deale but with theſe three kinds of death, hanging, ſtoning, burning. <hi>Dauid</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed fowre fould reſtitution of the ſtolne lamb, and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beſide the fellone to the death: wherein two wayes he ran before the law, and ſtrained it as it were a ſcrowle of parchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 1. For neyther was the crime capital: 2. neyther was the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to make ſo large a reſtitution. For the law caſe was this, If the theft were taken in the hand of the theef, he was to rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer it. If he had killed it or ſold it, he was but to reſtore fowre oxen for one, and fiue ſheep for one, now fowre fould are eight,
<pb facs="tcp:177636:12"/>the duplicate of the oxen. Neyther is there any exception to be made againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> as of this courſe were exorbitant from Iuſtice, or that he wringed or wronged gods lawe, it being the prerogatiue of his place, according to the circumſtances of the cryme, eyther to extentd or remit the puniſhment awarded by gods lawe. I may yeeld that you ſay truth, in your third reaſon, that nothing hath bin ſo miſerably abuſed, as the moſt ſacred ſigne of the Croſſe, and that from the beginning, while ſome haue adored it, and haue ſigned their breaſt and forehead, with it, as armour of proofe, againſt diuels and all miſhappes: and we confeſſe that the Chriſtians, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayth, at the firſt, did take the outward ſign of the Croſſe for a ſupine ſecurity for their indemnity. And <hi>Gregorie</hi> of Rome, in his 3 booke of <hi>Dialogues</hi> lendeth vs a lye, and that a luſty one, as hee hath peſtered that booke with a noyſome companie of very fabulous and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous things. A Iewe (ſayth he) entred by night into the temple of an Idoll, there to take his reſt, but agaſt at the ſight of ſo many euill ſpirits in that place, he armed himſelfe with the ſigne of the croſſe: now when the head deuil perceiued that a man was come, he diſpatched an vnder diuel vnto him to examine him, what he was, but when he had ſeen him he returned and ſayde. I found indeed an empty veſſell, but it was ſealed, and ſo left the Iewe and did him no harme: which while he recounted with himſelfe, he became a Chriſtian. Alſo we are not ignorant what ſlauer and blaſphemies haue been thrown vp to heauen, in their adorations and oriſons made to the Croſſe: as when they haue chaunted in this wiſe in their churches. <hi>O Crux aue ſpes vnica, Hoc paſſionis tempore, Auge piis iuſtitiam, Resſque dona ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam. All haile ô Croſſe, our onlie hope in this time of the paſſion, Increaſe in the godly righteouſneſſe, and giue pardon to the guiltie.</hi> All which words are the very vomit of an Aſpe. Againe, they roare in the congregation thus: <hi>Ecce ſignum cruc is venite ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus, Behold the roode of the Croſſe, let vs come and worſhip it.</hi> Which is horrible ſacriledge. Againe, thus they powre out the ſurcharge of their ſtomacks vpon the churches lap: Crucem tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am adoramus Domine reſurrectionem tuam ſanctam glorificamus.
<pb facs="tcp:177636:13"/>Where, they ſet the Croſſe in the higher roome, and make the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnderling vnto it. I dare not ſtir this deuiliſh dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill any more, leaſt I ſtifle your ſtomack. The ſacrificing ſhaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings drinke down deeplie this damnable opinion, and feede vpon it as vpon a reſtoratiue to the enchantment of their ſoules, that they conſecrate and ſanctifie all things, by the ſigne of the Croſſe. Thus we graunte, that neuer poore ſigne was ſo tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as the croſſe hath been: they hauing ſtretched euery ioynte thereof, vpon the rack of their moſt execrable blaſphemies. But what would you euict from hence? that therfore it is vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull to vſe the ſigne of the Croſſe at all? Then I deny your conſecution. For, is the vſe of a thing to be taken away for the abuſe ſake, that is caſt vpon it? then take away the Sunne out of the firmament, for that hath bin worſhipped: take awaye the Phyſicians ſawes and inſtruments, becauſe many dogleaches with their vnſkilfulneſſe haue abuſed them, to the ſpoyle of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Take away all weapons of warfare, and let vs goe naked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field againſt the enemy, becauſe many haue taken them vp againſt their countrie; take away wine and ſtrong drinke, becauſe more haue periſhed by that then by the ſword. Take away our wits, memory, health, ſtrength, and the whole man, be cauſe euery part, and the whole, is miſerably abuſed by vs all, through our ſins.</p>
                  <p>In your fourth reaſon you are wide, ſaying, that there is no vſe of the ſigne of the croſſe. For it is vſed in a grateful remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of Chriſt, and him crucified: whereby they woulde teſtifie, that they are not aſhamed of the croſſe of Chriſt. And that this was the chiefe conſideration in the vſe of this ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, ordained by the church, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his 8. ſermon, <hi>de verbis Apoſtoli</hi> ſheweth. For the Infidels inſulted ouer the Chriſtians, arguing them of follie, for worſhipping a crucified redeemer: whome that holy father anſwereth thus. <hi>Cor quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hahemus, non tamen quale vos habetis: nec pudet nos crucifixi; ſed in parte vbi ſignum pudoris eſt, ſignum crucis eius habemus. We haue a hearte, but not ſuch an one, as you haue: neither are we aſhamed of him that is crucified; but in that part where the ſigne of ſhame is, which is the
<pb facs="tcp:177636:13"/>forehead haue we the ſigne of his Croſſe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In Pſal. 141</note> In another place to the ſame purpoſe, he ſayth: <hi>Inſultet paganus crucifixo Chriſto, vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ego in frontibus regum crucem Chriſti. Quod irridet, ibi ſaluor. Nihil eſt ſuperbius agro, qui irridet medicame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum ſuum. Let the Pagan ouercrow chriſt, let me ſee in the foreheads of kings the croſſe of chriſt. That which he mocketh, ſaueth me, there is nothing prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then a ſicke man, which ſcorneth his medicin.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> In the ſame place he ſpeaketh thus: <hi>vſque adeo de cruce non erubeſco, vt non in oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culto loco habeam crucem Chriſti, ſed in fronteportem.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                     <hi>I am ſo little aſhamed of the croſſe of Chriſt, as</hi> I <hi>beare it not in a ſecret place, but in my forehead.</hi> Finally in the ſame place he ſayth: <hi>non habea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam frontem, tega team crux Domini mei. O let not me haue a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked forehead, but let the croſſe of my Lord couer it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>But now that cauſe is remooued, and we are all called Chriſtians, the ſigne of the croſſe which came in by that occaſion may be remooued.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Chriſt ſhall be the marke and white, that ſcorners ſhall ſhoote at to the worlds end. For <hi>Iulian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orphirie, Lucian,</hi> haue their progeny among vs, and <hi>Dauid</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nounceth him a bleſſed man, that hath not ſit in the chaire or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>omers. And <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> noddy that ſaith there is no god, or Sauiour Chriſt, liueth among vs. Wherfore for all this, this ceremony may continue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>And why may we not take vp ſom other ſigne and token, to remember Chriſt by, in the roome of this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>I know none ſo liuely as this: the ſigne of the croſſe being ſo naturally expreſſed in many of our actions: as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> doth obſerue: For ſeafaring men firſt ſet vp a maſte,<note place="margin">Ambroſe ſerm. 56.</note> and then ſpred a ſaile in forme of a croſſe, by which the ſea is broken. And the courſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution of the heauens, ſheweth vs ſuch a figure, diuiding it ſelfe into fowr parts, the Eaſt, Weſt, North, South, conteined as it were in the fowre corners of the croſſe. Alſo man in his going, when he lifteth vp his hand, is the very portaiture of a croſſe. Theſe be the conceits of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his wit: which albeit they prooue nothing, we ſhold not deſpiſe. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in their crownes and diademes, haue the engrauen image of the croſſe, to which cuſtome we muſt not impute any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition:
<pb facs="tcp:177636:14"/>becauſe by that ſigne they doo profeſſe and witneſſe, that they worſhip and maintaine the religion of Chriſt. For if it be lawfull for any Noble man to haue the ſcutchion and arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of his auntient houſe: it is alſo lawfull in the ſigne of the croſſe, to profeſſe Chriſts religion. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great did ſee the ſigne of the croſſe in the ayer, with this title and Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion added thereunto: <hi>Sub hoc ſigno vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ces: vnder this ſigne thou ſhalt get the victory.</hi> Thus god by miracle would ſtrengthen and confirme him in the truth of his religion, which he had newly entertayned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue giuen vs ſome authorities for the croſſe: as from <hi>Auguſtine, Ambroſe, Conſtantine.</hi> But then the times were more degenerate and corrupt. But can you giue vs teſtimonies, that make for the credit of it, within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of three hundred yeeres after chriſt, and in the plain ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of times before the myſtery of iniquity did beginne to worke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>I can and will. What ſay you to <hi>Iuſtine Martyr, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Origen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iuſtinus Martyr ad Orthodox os adquaeſt n 8.</note> who ſpeake moſt clearely, and are of our ſide in the cauſe of the croſſe? I will giue you their ſayings. <hi>Dextra manu in nomine Chriſti eos conſignamus, qui ſigillo tall indigent: with the right hand we ſigne them, in the name of chriſt, who ſtand in need of ſuch a ſeale, ſayth Iuſtine Martyr:</hi> And <hi>Cyprian</hi> twiſe ſpeaketh luculently enough to the point,<note place="margin">Cyprianus de vnitate eccleſiae.</note> in this manner. <hi>Ozias rex l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>prae varietate in fronte maculatus eſt, eaparte corporis nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, offenſo Domino, vbi ſignantur qui Dominum promerentur. King</hi> Vzza <hi>was ſmitten with the tokens and ſpots of leproſie, in his forehead, being dodded in that part of the body, god being diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in the which Chriſtians are conſigned with whome God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cyprianus ad Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trian: Orig. 8. ſet in diuerſos Ezech. 9.</note> And writing to <hi>Demetrian,</hi> he ſpeaketh of the regenerate who ſhall be conſigned by the croſſe. <hi>Origen</hi> is as playne, in the caſe, applying the marke of the letter <hi>Tau</hi> (of which the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſpeaketh, with which they were diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that were ſaued, when the Legatiue deſtroying Angels diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched by God had made a greate ſlaughter of others) to the ſigne of the croſſe, and indeede making it to bee that verye
<pb facs="tcp:177636:14"/>ſigne: <hi>quos T tau literaid eſt cruc is pictura ſignauerit, whome he ſigned with the letter T tau,</hi> that is the ſtampe and impreſſion of the croſſe. Further, if you pleaſe to heare <hi>Tertullian,</hi> he is no cold ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cate, and proctor in this point.<note place="margin">Tertullia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronamilit. Lib. 3. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cionem.</note> He doubteth not to ſay, <hi>Adla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cra, monſas, lumina, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bilia, ſedilia, quacunque nos co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatioexercet fronte crucis ſigno terimus.</hi> And writing againſt <hi>Marcion,</hi> he maketh the letter T <hi>tau,</hi> hitherto cited out of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell,</hi> to pretend and prefigure the ſigne of the Croſſe, which was afterward to be made in the forehead, when he ſayth, <hi>Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Tau eſt ſpecies crucis, quam portendebat futuram in frontibus noſtris.</hi> With theſe reuerend holy men of bleſſed memory, gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den mouthed <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> goeth hand in hand, in the behalfe of the Croſſe, ſpeaking thus woorthily:<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 16. mat. Hom. 55.</note> 
                     <hi>Quando te cruce ſignas magna tuam frontem arma ſiducia, libertate anima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> munias. When thou ſigneſt thy ſelfe with the croſſe, arme thy forehead with cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and quiet thy minde,</hi> Finally, from them to deſcend to Baſill, a Reuerend Father of very good regarde,<note place="margin">Baſilius cap. 27. de Sp. S.</note> he alloweth it for a lawful and laudable cuſtome, the vſe of the Croſſe, which was of good age and time, in his time. In a tractate, entitled of the holy ghoſt, excepting againſt ſuch that would confront and beare downe old cuſtomes, in that regarde that they had not warrant from the word, and there numbring the many inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences that wold ariſe from thence, he maketh this the formoſt hurtful conſequence in the rank, which ſheweth his good mind and affection to the croſſe: <hi>Siconſuetudines quae ſcrip to proditae non ſunt tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haud multum habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes momenti reiicimus, impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes &amp;c. da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>bimus, quae in Euangelio neceſſaria ad ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, vt ſigno crucis eos qui ſpem collocaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in chriſto ſignemus quis ſcripto docuit? If we ſhall caſt vp ſuch cuſtomes that the worde toucheth not, as matters of no ſuch quality and conſequence, we ſhal alſo indiſcreetly condemn ſuch things which are alſo accounted ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the goſpell.</hi> 1. <hi>for who hath charged vs by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that we ſign thoſe that put their truſt in chriſt with the ſigne of the cros?</hi> Thus you ſee how the fathers are for vs: ſo if you wil be ruled &amp; led by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſy is ended, &amp; we are good frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>But theſe Fathers flouriſhed in the prime age
<pb facs="tcp:177636:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177636:15"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177636:16"/>of the church, and as it were in the infancy and minoritie of the ſame. We haue all the light they could giue vs, but we haue ſeen more light ſince, and therfore I couet to haue the cauſe perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by the later writers. Haue you any ſtore of them of your ſide?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Without wrong doone to the learning of any, I dare auerre it that we haue as deepe men for learning &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as any you can name, that this age hath brought foorth, that are eyther patrones of the ceremonies of the Church of England, and particularly of the ceremonie of the croſſe, or elſe allowers of them, and approouers of the croſſe, acknowledging the libertye that the church hath, as to cancell them, ſo to keep them and leaue vs to this our lawfull liberty, no way ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to abridge vs of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>I would heare what they are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus. Peter Martyr,</speaker>
                  <p>whome I reuerence as much as any other, in his letter to Biſhop <hi>Hooper,</hi> and in three or fowre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther letters, that are extant, as alſo in ſundry other places of his woorthy works, all which I haue giuen thee in this treatiſe, as occaſion did yeeld, and therfore it ſhall be needleſſe to repeate his wiſe ſayings. <hi>Bucer</hi> that mighty learned man, as he eaſilye could digeſt the eſtabliſhed ceremonies of the reformed church in England, in the daies of that peerleſſe prince, and another <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, Edward</hi> the ſixt; ſo he thought ſpecially well of the croſſe, according as it may be lawfully vſed, and according as we vſe it, and theſe are his words.<note place="margin">Bucer.</note> 
                     <hi>Signum hoc no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tam quod eſt vſue in ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiis antiquiſſimi, quam quod eſt admodum ſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>x, &amp; praeſentis admonitionis crucis Chriſti, adhiberi nec indecens nec inutile ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimo: ſi adhibeatur modò purè intellectum, &amp; religioſe excipiatur, nulla nec ſuperſtitione adiuncta, nec elementi ſernitute, nec leuitate, aut vulgari conſuetudine. I do hould it not vnſeemly, or vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, that the ſigne of the croſſe ſhold be vſed: not ſo much becauſe it is of that long time and continuance in the church, as that it is of ſo good vſe, and tendeth to ſuch good end, as beeing moſt ſimple, and of preſent admonition, as putting vs in minde of the croſſe of chriſt: ſo it be rightlie vnderſtoode and religiouſly entertained,
<pb facs="tcp:177636:16"/>without any addition of ſuperſtition, or ſeruitude of the element, or leuity, or common cuſtome. Iuell</hi> that was the <hi>Iulium Sydus,</hi> and the Iewell of his time among vs, though he diſtaſteth the crowde of ceremonies, which were without meaſure,<note place="margin">Iuel. in Apolog.</note> throwne vpon the church, and were the ſurcharge thereof, in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> tyme, againſt which that holy Father did except: yet he allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the receiued ceremonies, now at this preſent day in vſe, in the church of England. I will acquainte you with his words. <hi>Concerning the multitude of ceremonies of idle and vaine nature, we knowe that Saint</hi> Auguſtine <hi>did much complaine of them in his time: and therefore wee haue greatlie diminiſhed the number of them, becauſe wee knowe that they were troubleſome to good conſciences, and too burthenſome to the church. Yet we retaine and haue liking not onely of thoſe ceremonies, which we are ſure were deliuered vs from the Apoſtles: but ſome others too beſides, which we thought might be ſuffered without hurt to the church of God: becauſe we affected, that all things in the congregation, might according to the will of the Apoſtle, bee doone with comlyneſſe and good order. But all ſuch things which wee perceiued to leane to ſuperſtition, or to be of no vſe, or bald, or toyiſh, or againſt the ſacred ſcriptures, or elſe vnmeet for ſober &amp; wiſe people, whereof there is a confuſed chaos, in the Romiſh ſinagogue, all theſe we haue vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly renounced and caſt off, becauſe we would not haue the worſhip of god confounded, and combred with ſuch follies.</hi> Whom wold not the euen cariage of this ſo worthy &amp; fine a Biſhop mooue? For my part I will ſuſpect ten thouſand mens iudgements, that are of your ſide: before I ſhall yeeld to thinke amiſſe of that man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>But you doe tell me but of thoſe of this church of England that applaude and approoue your opinions: but do any of the learned men beyond the ſeas, runne with you in that mind?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>That worthy man <hi>Theodore Beza,</hi> though I finde him no great friend to the croſſe: yet hee miſliketh not, that ſuch churches as retayne it, ſhould keepe their liberty therein, theſe being his words in his anſwer to <hi>Frances Baldwin.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bezae reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponſio ad F. Bald.</note> 
                     <hi>Scio no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullos f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>blat a crucis adoratione, aliquem ſignt crucis vſum retinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe:
<pb facs="tcp:177636:17"/>vt antur igitur ipſi ſicut par eſt ſua libertate. I know that many make ſome vſe of the ſigne of the croſſe, taking away all ſuperſtition from it: Let ſuch as it is meet vſe theyr liberty.</hi> In the ſame place immediately before, the ſame learned Father ſayth, <hi>Fuerit ſane tempus quo fuit aliquis iſtius ſignaculi aduerſiu chriſti crucifixt contemptores vſus: ſit etiam diu &amp; libenter à chriſtianis, vſurpatus pro externa verae religionis profeſſione. There was a time that there was ſome vſe of this ſign, againſt the contemners of chriſt crucifica: &amp; let it be a long time &amp; willingly taken vp of chriſtians, for the outward profeſſion of true religion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heming. in 1. Cap. Ioh. Zanchius de baptiſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Hemingius</hi> in the firſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vpon <hi>Iohn</hi> ſayth: <hi>Minime improbo ſignum crucis: I doo not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowe of the ſigne of the croſſe.</hi> Thus you ſee how we would ſauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie you in your mind, euery way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>Though you have prooued the vſe of the croſſe out of many authors: yet you ſhew not that it was vſed in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: I wiſh you ſhould prooue that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſaye you to <hi>Tertulliau,</hi> who ſpeaking of the ſigne of the Croſſe,<note place="margin">Aduerſus Marcionè. lib. 3. De praeſcript. ad. uerſus hae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reticos.</note> there withall toucheth the ſacraments of the church. thus coupling them together: <hi>Quae omnia cum in te quoque deprchendantur &amp; ſignaculum frontium, &amp; eccleſiarum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta.</hi> I would alſo you ſhold wel waigh theſe words of the ſame father: <hi>Sed quae itur a quo intellectus interpretetur coru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae aduerſus hareſes faciunt? A diabolo ſcilicet, cuius ſunt partes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruertendi veritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qui ipſas quoque res ſacramentoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuinoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in idoloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myſteriis aemulatur. Fing it &amp; ipſe quoſdam, vtique cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes &amp; fideles ſuos: expiatione peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de lauacro repromit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it, &amp; ſic initiat mithrae: ſignat ille in frontib us milites ſuos: celebrat &amp; panis oblatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tertul: de reſurrecti. one carnis</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; imagine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> refurrectionis inducit.</hi> I alſo charge you with this his other ſaying: <hi>Caro abluitur vt anima emacule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: caro vngitur vt anima conſecretur: caro ſignatur vt &amp; anima muniatur: caro manus impoſitione adumbratur, vt &amp; anima spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu illuminetur: caro corpore &amp; ſanguine Chriſti veſcitur, vt &amp; anima deo ſaginetur.</hi> But moſt plaine and plauſible is this ſpeech of <hi>Origen:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Origen in Pſal, 8 Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>. 2. To. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.1</note> 
                     <hi>Vt ergo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exprobremur ab inſipiente, conuertamus nos ob omitibus iniquitatibus noſtris: ne deprehendens in nobis maculas pecca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orum ideſt ſuae voluntatis inſignia exprobret &amp; dicat; Ecce
<pb facs="tcp:177636:17"/>hic Chriſtianus dicebatur &amp; ſigno Chriſti ſignabatur in fronte me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as autem volun tates &amp; mea chirographa gerebat in corde. Ecc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile qui mih: &amp; meis operibus renuntiauit in baptiſmo, meis rur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum operibus ſe inſeruit, meiſque legibus paret. Liberati ergo ab omnibus inquitatibus, ſtude amus ne in die Iudicij, huiuſmodi op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>briis inſpientes diabols ſuccumbamus. That we may not be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided by the diuell, let vs depart from all our iniquities, leaſte finding in vs the ſpottes of ſinnes, that is the badge and enſignes of his will, he thus checke and choake vs, ſaying: Behold, this man was called a Chriſtian, and was ſigned with the ſigne of Chriſt in his forehead but my will and handwriting was in his hart: Behold, this man who forſooke me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and al my works in baptiſme, hath again wrapped himſelfe in my workes, and obeyed my lawe. Wherefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deliuered from all iniquities, let vs haue a care that in the day of iudgement, we be not ouercom of the reproachful ſpeeches of this fooliſh diuell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>Know you any further regard had in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of this ceremony?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>Our forefathers alluded herein to the old cuſtome of the Iewes, who were commaunded to ſprinkle the poſtes of their houſes with the bloud of the Paſchall lamb: now our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, according to this ſimilitude, ſigned the forehead with the Croſſe, becauſe the other legall ceremonie ceaſed, and they might not ſacrifice after the comming of Chriſt. This reaſon <hi>Auguſtin</hi> toucheth, in his book <hi>De catechizandis rudibus,</hi> in the 20. chapter. <hi>Chriſti paſſio in illo populo figurata eſt, cùm iusſi ſunt ouem occidere &amp; manducare, &amp; de ſanguine eius poſtes ſuos ſignare, &amp; hoc celebrare omni anno: Cuius pasſionis &amp; crucis ſigno in fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hodie tanquam in poſte ſignandus es omneſque Chriſtiani ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur. Chriſt his pasſion was figured in that people, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were commanded to kill the lamb, and eate, and to ſigne their poſtes with the bloud therof, and to celebrate that euery yeer: With which ſigne if his pasſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; croſſe, thou art at this day, ſigned in the forehead as in a poſt, &amp; ſo are al chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be ſigned.</hi> This he further preſſeth in the very be ginning of the 26, chapter of the ſame book, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>vtique fignandus eſt, &amp; eccleſiae more tractandas: Hee is</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177636:18"/>to bee ſigned and handled according to the order of the Church. Thus are all your former reaſons aunſwered, and they fall before the face of better inſtaunces as Dagon before the arke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus.</speaker>
                  <p>But we ſhould rather beare chriſt crucified in our heartes then to profeſſe him in this bare and outwarde ſigne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Irenaeus.</speaker>
                  <p>I know that the power and vertue of the croſſe is not in the externall ſigne, but in the internall faith, which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hold of Chriſt, nayled vpon the croſſe: but it pleaſeth god to teache his church by outward ſignes, God willeth <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiell,</hi> to take a ſcrippe,<note place="margin">Ezech. 12,</note> a ſtaffe, ſhooes like a wayfaring man, in token that he ſhould bee a baniſhed man. The ſame Prophet by two tables which he ioyneth together,<note place="margin">Ezech. 37,</note> foreſheweth that the kingdome of <hi>Iſraell</hi> and <hi>Iudah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſay. 20,</note> ſhall be conſolidated, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one poeple. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> by going barefoote, teacheth <hi>Aegypte</hi> and <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> that ſo they ſhall goe in their captiuity. <hi>Ieremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> by bearing yoakes and fetters,<note place="margin">Ierem. 27,</note> and ſending them to the kinges of <hi>Edom, Moab, Ammon, Tyrus, Sydon, Iudah,</hi> giueth them a viſible and palpable ſigne of their indurance in Babylon. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſeus</hi> willeth <hi>Ioas</hi> king of Iſraell,<note place="margin">2 King. 13,</note> who came to viſite him in his ſickneſſe, to take vp a bowe and arrowes, thereby prophecying victory ouer the Aſſyrians,<note place="margin">1. King. 11,</note> vnto him. The Prophet <hi>Ahiah</hi> rent <hi>Ieroboams</hi> new cloake in twelue parts, willing <hi>Ieroboam</hi> to take ten of them in ſigne of the rent that the Lord had made of the kingdome of <hi>Salomon</hi> into twelue parts, whereof tenne of them ſhould deuolue to <hi>Ieroboam.</hi> Chriſt willeth his diſciples to ſhake off the duſt from their feet,<note place="margin">Math. 10,</note> taken in that houſe, where the word of God offered was deſpiſed, in teſtimoniall of this preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Math, 18.</note> Chriſt checketh and conuinceth the ambition of his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, by ſetting a little child in the midſt of them.<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.</note> Hee waſhed his diſciples feet, by that ſigne reading them a lecture of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and charity.<note place="margin">Acts. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>Agabus</hi> taking <hi>Pauls</hi> girdle in hand, ſaide: <hi>So ſhall this man be bound that oweth this girdle.</hi> The very heathens vſed this kind of learning, to teach &amp; aduertiſe by outward ſigns <hi>Scyllurus ſcytha</hi> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> being at the point of deth exhorteth
<pb facs="tcp:177636:18"/>his children to concord in many graue wordes; but at laſt, by a ſheffe of arrowes bound together, which afterward he ſeueted, he ſhewed the difference betweene Vnitie and Diuiſion: It is the ſaying of the Poet <hi>Horace;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Segnius irritant animos demiſſa per aures,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quàm quae ſunt oculis ſubiecta fidelibus, &amp; quae</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ipſe ſibi tradit ſpectator —</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Wherefore Chriſt inſtituted the ſacrament of his body, that not onely the eares might be inſtructed in the myſterie of our redemption, but that all the ſenſes elſe ſhould be ſtirred vppe thereby. The ſigne of the Croſſe therefore in the childes fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head is outwardly inſtructiue, as the Croſſe of Chriſt is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually inſtructiue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antim:</speaker>
                  <p>To admitte all that you haie ſaide, how ſhall I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the weaker forte, that will cake offence at my conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and forſake my doctrine? This is a very ſharpe thorne to my ſides, and troubleth me very much, whilſt I conſider what the apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith; <hi>It is good neither to eate fleſh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 14.21</note> 
                     <hi>nor to drinke wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother ſtumbleth, or is offended, or made weake.</hi> And the apoſtle walked ſo warily this way, as hee tooke this ſolemne bond of proteſtation of himſelfe;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.13.</note> 
                     <hi>If meate offend my brother, I wil eate no fleſh while the world ſtandeth, that I may not offend my brother.</hi> What ſay you to this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren:</speaker>
                  <p>This rule of charitie the apoſtle giueth, is of neceſſary obſeruation. But wee muſt putte a difference betweene thoſe that are weake; firſt, in a ſimplicity: ſecondly, obſtinacie. If they be obſtinately and wilfully weake; wee are not to hang vpon their ſleeues, or to feede their humours, but to giue them ouer, though they be as hote as a toaſte againſt vs; for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity preſcribeth not the truth. <hi>Amicus Plato, amicus Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, magis amica veritas. Plato is my friend, and Socrates is my friend, but the trueth is the greateſt friend of all. Veritas Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orum eſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ichri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Helena Graecorum: Trueth among Chriſtians is more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Helen among the Graecians.</hi> The Scribes and Phariſies were thus preuiſhly and peruerſly offended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:177636:19"/>Chriſt &amp; his diſciples, but he weied it not a ruſh, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Diſciples to ſhake them off:<note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>Let them alone, they are the blind leaders of the blind.</hi> And he aduertiſed them to take heed of the leauen of the Phariſies. Neither did he regard the froward and vntoward Iewes; neither the Apoſtles the eluiſh compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and we are taught by Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Iohn.</note> not to affoorde ſo much as the curteſie of our lippes, to bid them <hi>God ſpeede.</hi> What al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the whole broode of Papiſts take offence at vs, becauſe we deteſt their abhominable Maſſes, and damnable idolatries, and obiect to vs theſe rules of the Apoſtle? Becauſe we haue a Canon to the contrary, That we muſt not doe euill that good may come of it; and the Apoſtle in the former Leſſons onely aymeth at offences that ariſe out of matters indifferent. We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde not what they ſay; we are tyed to none, but to thoſe that are weake in a zealous ſimplicity, whoſe ſoares we are to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with a ſofte hand; and to ſuch onely did the Apoſtle apply himſelfe. Otherwiſe hee proteſted and profeſſed the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, That hee was no man-pleaſer; <hi>If I ſhould pleaſe men,</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>I were not the ſeruant of God.</hi> The harueſt of offences are ſo great, and of ſuch contrary courſe, as I know not what Sicle is able to cut them downe. Some are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Giant in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Samuel</hi> that haue too many fingers on a hand:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Sam. 21.</note> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are like <hi>Adonibeze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k</hi> in the Booke of <hi>Iudges,</hi> who had his fingers and toes cutte off.<note place="margin">Iudg. 1.</note> Some would cloy the Church with an importable and exceſſiue weight of Ceremonies, and ſo are offenſiue in their exceſſe: Others would haue them all doone away, and offend in the defect; and the vulgar people, whome we ſeeke ſo to pleaſe, are conſtant in no thing ſo much, as in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie, as the Moone, the Riuer <hi>Euripus,</hi> and <hi>Protens,</hi> that turneth himſelfe into all ſhapes. Shew thou thy ſelfe a worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that neede not be aſhamed, and diuide the worde aright; walke with a right foote in the way of thy vocation, by euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte and good reporte, and ſtand not thou vpon the mercies of mens lippes: <hi>It is a ſmall thing</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paule</hi>) <hi>for mee to be iudged of you. Noah</hi> goeth for a Preacher of righteouſneſſe, though hee was flowted of the firſt world for the ſtructure of
<pb facs="tcp:177636:19"/>the Arke <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhall goe for a godly wiſeman, dauncing before the Lord in a linnen Ephod,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.5. 2. Sam. 6. Acts 26.</note> though <hi>Michol</hi> his wife malepertly befoole him for his labour. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh nothing but wordes of ſobrietie; howſoeuer <hi>Feſtus</hi> miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>termeth them as he pleaſe in his partiall opinion, and giue them to his madnes. As the Tai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor ſhapeth not a garment to another mans pleaſure, but to the liking of him onely for whome hee maketh it: ſo the Preacher is onely to regarde to pleaſe God, whoſe ſeruant hee is, and not to frame himſelfe to euery ones fancie. When wrong is done to any in a lower Court, his remedie is, to appeale to a higher: this courſe are we to take when mens tongues walke thorowe our actions, as they pleaſe, and their wordes are as prickings of ſwordes; we make prouocation from their ſiniſter cenſure to the iuſt tribunall ſeate of Gods moſt ſacred maieſtie; yet God forbid but that wee ſhould haue a ſpeciall care of ſuch that are weak in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, &amp; giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medicine to heale their wounds, and ſay with the Apoſtle; <hi>Who is weake and I am not weake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Wherefore, it eſſentially appertaineth to the Miniſters office to inſtruct ſuch; and to trauell with them in the way of infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, vntill hee hath ſtrengthened them, and ſet them vpon their feete. And if their offence growe from the ceremonies of our Church, they are to be taught the vſe and nature of them: I. as firſt, that they are things indifferent, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lawfull with theſe qualifications; firſt, that there be no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition in them: ſecondly, no iuſt matter of ſcandall: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no opinion of merite, or matter of religion repoſed in them: fourthly, that the Church be not oppreſſed with the multitude of them as it was in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>119.</hi> ad Ianuarium.</note> that godly father complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, That the ſtate of the Iewes, in compariſon of theirs, was eaſier, and more tolerable: 2. They alſo are to be taught what force the Lawes of the Church are of, to the binding of the conſciences. That they are of ſuch qualitie, as they bind them not; ſo as we caſt no contempt vpon them: ſecondly, giue no offence: thirdly, or in an inſolent ſingularitie violate them: fourthly, or vnjoynt, or diſſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, the common ſettled governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and peace of the Church: with theſe cautions firſt obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb facs="tcp:177636:20"/>the conſcience is not bound.<note place="margin">Acts 15.29.</note> As for examples The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles gaue out a decree, That the Gentiles that were conuerted vnto Chriſt, ſhould abſtaine from that which was ſtrangled, from blood, from that which was offered to an Idoll: in the which conſtitution, they aymed at nothing but the peace of the Church. For otherwiſe there could haue beene no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betweene the Iewes and the Gentiles. If a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breach of the common peace, had eaten of any of thoſe, hee hadde not ſinned againſt his conſcience. For otherwiſe <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith;<note place="margin">Acts 15.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Why tempt yee God, to lay a yoke vpon the Diſciples neckes, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 2.16. Matth. 15.11</note> And <hi>Paule</hi> ſaieth; <hi>Let no man condemne you in meate and drinke.</hi> And Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>That which entreth into the mouth defileth not the man.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Paul</hi> ſaieth, <hi>Whatſoeuer is ſolde in the Shambles,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.25.</note> 
                     <hi>eate yee, and aske no question:</hi> Thus is the vſe of them, Ciuill and Politique: So that wee haue the warrant of a good conſcience to conforme our ſelues vnto them. 3. Let the people likewiſe be informed, that they are appoynted for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and decencie ſake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and how needful it is, that this order and comelines ſhould be kept, according to the ſtreight direction of the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.40.</note> 
                     <hi>Let all things be done honeſtly, and by order.</hi> The inhibitions of the Lawe, That no man ſhould ſowe his ground with mixed ſeedes: That beaſts of diuerſe kindes, as the oxe and the aſſe ſhould not goe together in the plow;<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.</note> that no man ſhould weare a garment of confected ſubſtances, as linnen and woollen; ſhoote and driue at the vnitie and vniformitie of the Church of God, and beare downe flatly diuiſion and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Leuit. 1.</note> The parts of the Calfe that were to be offered vppe for an oblation and ſacrifice were orderly diſpoſed and beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar, a pile of wood being firſt fitly laide, at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in <hi>Aegipt</hi> feaſting his bretheren, had an eſpeciall eye to order, placing them in their ranckes at the Table,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 43. Luke 9.</note> ſeating euery one according to their age. Chriſt himſelfe approoued this courſe of order, and as duely practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, feeding the people miraculouſly in the wilderneſſe, and placing them by equall Companies, by fifties in a rowe.</p>
                  <p>I might alſo returne your owne obiection againſt you, as a
<pb facs="tcp:177636:20"/>reaſon to induce this conformitie in caſes ceremoniall: for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences are as vſually taken at the omitting them, as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them, which the Saintes of God very well perceiuing, haue yeelded to the times, and haue abridged themſelues of their lawfull libertie, thereby alſo to bring the more benefite to the Church of God. For this cauſe, (as the Goſpel noteth) our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt paide pole-money for himſelfe and Peter; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as being King and God, and the true Meſſias, hee was free by law, and exempted from the tribute. He kept the common cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome for auoiding of offence: <hi>Lest we ſhould offend them, go to the ſea, and cast in an angle, and take the firſt fiſh that commeth vp; and when thou haſt opened his mouth, thou ſhalt finde a peece of twentie pence, that take, and giue it vnto them for me and thee.</hi> Yet in his queſtion before to <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 17.17.</note> he had ſhewed his diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Of whom do the Kings of the earth take tribute or pole-mony? Of their children or of ſtrangers?</hi> Thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated himſelfe to the ſeaſons in circumciſing <hi>Timothie,</hi> whilſt he conſidered how gaineſome it would be to the weaker ſort.<note place="margin">Acts 16.3.</note> The ſame Apoſtle ſhaued his head in <hi>Cenchrea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 21.26.</note> and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained purifications according to the Law, becauſe he ſaw how that courſe would ſatisfie the weaker ſort, to toll them on to Chriſt. And this was the vſuall practiſe of this Apoſtle in a ſubtile wiſedome, which our Sauour Chriſt commendeth to his apoſtles in this peece of precept:<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Be as wiſe as Serpents.</hi> And ſo much he teſtifieth of himſelfe, ſaying; <hi>To the Iewes I become as a Iew, that I may winne the Iewes: to them that are vnder the law, as though I were vnder the Law,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>that I may winne them that are vnder the Law: to them that are without the Law, as though I were without the Law, that I may winne them that are without the Law: to the weake I become as weake, that I may winne the weake: I am made all things to all men, that I might by all meanes ſaue ſome.</hi> From this enſample and ſaying of the Apoſtle, I diſpute thus: If the Apoſtle held it ſo expedient; to the better inſinuating himſelfe into the ſoules of his people, to beget them to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to repeate repealed ceremonies, and to renew them, being quite out of date: the conſequence is not to be rebuked that we
<pb facs="tcp:177636:21"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177636:21"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177636:22"/>inferre vpon it; that wee may as well admit of indifferent cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which candide ſimplicity firſt deliuered to the Church many ages fore-paſt, which the Church hath ſtill continued. This was <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his politique pietie and precept, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſheweth in an epiſtle to <hi>Ianuarius; Si non vultis errare facit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quod ego ſoleo.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarium.</note> 
                     <hi>Ego enim ad quamcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eccleſiam venis ad eius ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias me accommodo. If yee will not doe amiſſe, follow my courſe. For to what Church I come, I applie my ſelfe to the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies thereof.</hi> For the Church is not to be depriued of her liberty, which Chriſt would haue alwaies to be preſerued whole, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any maime or iniurie done vnto it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Autim.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſeeme to diſagree with your owne ſelfe: for whereas you make theſe matters but indifferent, by your ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt taking their part, you force them from their nature, and vrge them as neceſſary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>In themſelues they are indifferent, but the Chriſtian Magiſtrate commanding them, whom wee ſtand bound to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey for conſcience ſake, I hold them neceſſarie to be obſerued. Lawes &amp; Obedience are the two feete that beare vp the bodie, both of the politique and ſpirituall ſtate, and the two armes that feede it and defend it. If the lawes had not beene in theſe caſes alreadie made, I ſhould neuer, for my owne part, wiſh to haue them made: but ſeeing wee haue now ſuch preſcription for them, and they are ſtill enioyned vs, I ſhall not be one to marre them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Autius.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot yet perſwade my ſelfe to yeelde vnto you, becauſe I am at ſuch ſtrife with my ſelfe, becauſe heeretofore I haue with-ſtood them, and haue beene ſo bitter againſt them: the ceremonies hitherto haue beene my declamation, and the ſtaffe and ſtuffe of many of my ſermons. Now what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them if I ſhall ſubſcribe? I ſhall ſeeme to looke vnder the brow, to wagge with the times, and to halte with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>If you haue exceeded your bounds heerein, come into the way. <hi>Humanum eſt errare:</hi> It is not a motion againſt nature to erre. <hi>Bernardus non vidit Om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ia, &amp; quand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>qú<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>xu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mitat
<pb facs="tcp:177636:22"/>Homerus.</hi> The Prophets of God haue beene deceiued in their opinions, and they haue beene ignorant in ſome things. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> encouraged <hi>Dauid</hi> in his intendment of building God a Temple,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 7.3.</note> whenas it was no part of the Lords meaning: but his will was. that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhould performe it. <hi>Samuel,</hi> though a great Prophet,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.</note> and the Lord was with him, and ſuffered not any of his words to drop to the ground; yet his iudgement de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued him, when he was ſent to annoint one of the ſons of <hi>Iſhai,</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. King. 4.27.</note> and made his eye his Counſellor, making choice of <hi>Eliab,</hi> becauſe he was the eldeſt, faireſt, and higheſt. When a ſuppliant woman came before <hi>Elizeus,</hi> caſting downe her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at his feete, and his ſeruant <hi>Giezi</hi> would haue thruſt her away; <hi>Elizeus</hi> ſaid, <hi>Let her alone, for her ſoule is vexed within her, and the Lord hath hid it from mee, and hath not tolde it mee.</hi> It is the ſaying of the Apoſtle <hi>Paule; We knowe but in parte, and we prophecie but in parte. Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> at euery viſion they had, prayed that God would reueale the meaning of it to them. The reaſon heereof is, the will of God that hath his dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and varietie of giftes. To be ledde with a ſtrict tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of opinion, becauſe wee haue dwelt a long time in it, and haue maintained it with ſtiffeneſſe of affection; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it is checked with better reaſon, it is wilfulneſſe, and not wiſedome, and the very common diſeaſe of Nature. This was <hi>Dauids</hi> diſpoſition, which nature ſolitarie in him, without grace ſuggeſted, not to reuerſe his ſentence of Lawe, awarded againſt <hi>Mephib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſheth,</hi> vppon falſe crimination of <hi>Siba</hi> againſt him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it afterward appeared as cleere as the Sunne,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6. 2. Sam. 19.</note> that hee had puniſhed him wrongfully. Contented hee was to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the iudgement vppon this full aduertiſement, that <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi> and he ſhould halfe the lands betweene them; hee would in no wiſe repeale that which hee had once pronounced. Such a one was <hi>Pilate,</hi> who would not alter any thing he had written, but ſaide; <hi>That which I haue written, I haue written.</hi> We ſhew our ſelues <hi>Pilates,</hi> rather than Prelates, in being wedded to our willes as vnto a wife, they two beeing in one fleſh. It is the ſaying of Saint <hi>Ambroſe, Inter ſeruos Chriſti contentio non debet
<pb facs="tcp:177636:23"/>eſſe ſed collatio: Not contention, but conference ought to be among the ſeruants of Chriſt.</hi> And it is well ſaide of <hi>Bernard; Paco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> contemnentes, &amp; gloriam quaerentes, pacem perdunt &amp; gloriam.</hi> Such as deſpiſe peace, and ſeeke glory, they ſhall looſe both their peace and their glorie. Our betters haue not bluſhed to recant their errours. <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> the greateſt among the bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of men (the Sonne of man onely excepted) was perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily reſolued with himſelfe, in the height of his humilitie, not to ſuffer Chriſt ſo to abaſe himſelfe to him, as to take his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of him,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.</note> when he anſwered him, <hi>I haue neede to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed of thee, and commest thou to mee?</hi> But when Chriſt had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to thoſe wordes, hee left his former purpoſe, and yeelded to Chriſts will. So <hi>Peter</hi> was fully determined with himſelfe, not to ſuffer Chriſt to ſtoope to waſh his feete, telling him to his face;<note place="margin">Iohn 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt neuer waſh my feete.</hi> But when Chriſt had rounded him in the care ſaying; <hi>If I waſh thee not, thou ſhalt haue no parte with me:</hi> Then here ſigned his former reſolution, and was as forward as before he had bin backeward, ſaying to him; <hi>Lord, not my feete onely, but alſo the hands and the head. Dauid</hi> had taken a ſolemne othe of himſelfe,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 25.</note> to cutte off roote and branch from the ſtocke of <hi>Nabal,</hi> euen euery one that made water a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wall, not meaning belike to ſpare his dog: yet by the timely interuenient mediation of <hi>Abigail,</hi> he was ſo charmd &amp; warmed with ſuch coles of kindnes as were caſt vpon his head, as his blood grew cooler, and hee forſooke his othe, and bleſſed God for it. It is a wiſe mans parte, not to looſe his care with <hi>Malchus,</hi> but to open it to good aduiſe and counſell. Counſel (as <hi>Plato</hi> in his Dialogues ſaith) is a ſacred thing. And it is well ſpoken of <hi>Minutius</hi> in <hi>Liuie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Saepe ego audiui milites, cum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſſe virum qui ipſe conſulit, quid in rem ſit: ſecundum cum qui bene monenti obediat. I haue often heard (my Souldiers ſaieth hee) that he is the rare man that is able to miniſter beſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>unſaile to himſelfe in all occurrences: and that he is next vnto him that enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth good counſell.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero pro Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entio.</note> The like ſaying hath <hi>Tullie</hi> in his Oration <hi>pro Cluentio; Sapientiſſimun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> eſſe dicunt, cui quid opus ſit, ipſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niat in mentem: proxime accedere ilium qui alterius bere viuentis
<pb facs="tcp:177636:23"/>obtemperat.</hi> Hee is accompted the wiſeſt man, who can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetue with himſelfe what is beſt for him: and ſecond to him, is hee that will be ruled by his beſt counſeller. It is our beſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to diſtruſt our owne learning and iudgement, and not to ſtand vpon termes of precedency and ſufficiency aboue others, but to liſten to our inferiours, when they ſpeake to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to <hi>Iethro</hi> a Madianite and Heathen: and as <hi>Naaman</hi> the Syrian did to the counſell of his ſeruantes.<note place="margin">Exod. 18. 2. King. 6.</note> Now <hi>Antimachus,</hi> if thou wilt take this courſe, I will bring thee out of thy former ſweate which thy conceit of thy former doings hath caſt thee into, and doe thee much good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antimachus</speaker>
                  <p>You haue ſpoken much of my retracting my error, and of apprehenſion of better counſell. I will aske you afterward, what is that counſell that you would I ſhoulde fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe? in the meane time, you that lay imputation of errour vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mee, doe you thinke the outward gouernement of your Church ſo abſolute, as it is not to be charged or touched with errour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren:</speaker>
                  <p>I will not ſay ſo: For Chriſt compareth the Church to a drawe nette, which bringeth to land with the good fiſh,<note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> all kinde of gatherings, with the pelfe and baggage of the ſoyle. To a field wherein the enemie ſcattereth his tares amiddeſt the good corne, which the husbandman hath ſowne. In many things wee offend all, ſaith holy <hi>Iames,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.</note> The prayer of the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Prophet to God, is, That he would not call him to reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his ignorances.<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> caſteth the lie vpon the very nature of vs; <hi>Euery man is a liar.</hi> If the Church might not be blacked with this coale of errour and ſinne, the Church ſhould not neede, by daily prayer, to begge at Gods hand remiſſion of ſinnes: Errours growe vppe as naturally in the Church, as wilde and luxurious weedes growe vppe in a garden among good hearbes.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> The Church that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of, without ſpot and wrinckle, is not the church Militant in earth, as the fooliſh Anabaptiſtes haue conceiued; but the church Triumphant in Heauen, which is in this perfect beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, God wiping away all teares from her eyes. Wherefore it
<pb facs="tcp:177636:24"/>is an idle queſtion that is mooved, <hi>Whether the Church can erre?</hi> So farre foorth as it heareth and followeth the woorde, and keepeth her faith whole and ſound to her husband, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre and goe out of the way. But becauſe it often feedeth vppon her owne fancies, and truſteth too much to her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe opinions, it can not otherwiſe be, but that ſhee ſhoulde forget herſelfe, and treade awrie. Finally it often ſo falleth out, that hogges and aſſes haue prefecture and chiefeſt place in the Church, who wallow in the puddle of prodigious errours, and maintaine moſt groſſe and ſottiſh ſuperſtitions. This was the caſe and face of the church in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> his time,<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.</note> when hee complaineth, that their ſiluer was become droſſe, and their wine was mixed with water. In Chriſt his time, the title of the church was with the Iewes: In which, though the Virgine <hi>Marie, Ioſeph, Zacharie, Elizabeth, Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Anna</hi> liued vprightly, and they beare this good report in the Goſpel, that they walked in all the commaundements of God without reproofe, the worlde being not able greatly to charge them with errours of manners; yet ſome were among them, whome common ignorance did miſ-leade; and others whom the impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of the Sadduces did bewitch,<note place="margin">1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> as they deuoured their ranke and wicked errours. And we know what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaieth, That men builde vppon the foundation Ieſus Chriſt, golde, ſiluer, pretious ſtones, timber, hay, ſtubble, which ſhall vndergoe the fire of Gods triall, and periſh, the foundation remaining ſure. Wee eaſily therefore yeelde, that there may be things amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in our Church-gouernement, and I doe wiſh of God they were, and God (no doubt) when the time commeth, will put his hands to this worke, maugre Sathans heart, that hindereth it all hee may. In the meane while it ſhall vvell become vs, to waite his leiſure, and not to preſcribe God his ſeaſon, and to ſay; <hi>It is time that thou haue mercie vppon Sion, yea the time is come.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 22. Prou. 25.11.</note> Our inuectiues againſt the preſent State, are as muſike in mourning; they muſt be reſerued to other times, that they may be as golden Apples with pictures of ſiluer. When <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſilaus</hi> the Philoſopher vvas ſolicited to diſpute amongſt the
<pb facs="tcp:177636:24"/>cuppes in the time of a great Banquet: hee refuſed it, ſaying; That it was in the rules of his Philoſophie, to knovve the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of time for euery thing. Bleſſe wee the name of his ſacred maieſtie for the <hi>Alcion</hi> dayes and times wee now enioy, and theſe yeeres of the right hand of the moſt High, wherein, as in the dayes of <hi>Salomon,</hi> wee ſit ſecurely vnder our vines and figge trees, without feare of the enemy. The Lorde hath long bleſſed vs vvith peace vnder a nurſing Queene; and hee yet lengthening the time thereof vnder our nurſing King, ſo that wee are the ſpectacle in the Stage of this Worlde, of a happie people, for all men to vvonder at. Our forefathers deſired to ſee theſe dayes, and could not ſee them; vvee haue them, and are glutted vvith them, and turne this grace of God into vvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, niceneſſe and eluiſhneſſe. The ſtrong man the Pope, the Hammer of the Church, is (thanked be God) quite out of poſſeſſion, and hee ſhall as ſoone vvring <hi>Hercules</hi> Clubbe out of his handes, if hee vvere aliue, as get footing againe here; the Lord ſauing his annoynted King <hi>Iames,</hi> and his ſacred Queen, the fruitefull Vine of his Church, and vertuous Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi> the royall plant of the Lordes hand, the doubled hope of the Churches tranquilitie. <hi>Baals</hi> Altars are throvvne dovvne, we haue the ſame Catholique doctrine in the Church in all points (I will put it to the iudgement of the wranglingeſt Anabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall vrchin that is) that Chriſt the wiſedome of his Father hath deliuered, the Primitiue Church preached, and the holy Martires haue confirmed with their blood. Is not this verie vvell for the time? O happy men if vve knewe our happines! which <hi>Carendo potius quam fruendo,</hi> wee muſt be brought to knowe. Goe vvith Creſſet and Torch light throughout all the Churches of the worlde, and tell mee vvhether from the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Circumference, there be ſuch a one as ours, in pietie, and proſperitie. When you haue ſounded and fadomed them all by a right line and plummet, you ſhall haue cauſe to ſay; <hi>This is my ſeate,</hi> heere will I dwell, becauſe I haue a delight in it. This is the <hi>Eden</hi> and choſen Garden of the Lorde our God, and the <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that is, the beautie of the whole worlde.
<pb facs="tcp:177636:25"/>Heere <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke floateth vppon the waters, whereas other Barkes and Keeles doe ſincke. Heere <hi>Aarons</hi> Rodde buddeth and bringeth forth Almonds. This Church is the Apple of the eye, the Diamond of the ring, the Hart of the bodie, a vine planted in a fruitefull place: the Seale vppon the right hand of God, the writing in the palme of his hand, as the day ſtarre in the middeſt of cloudes round abour vs, as the Moone when ſhee is at the full, as the floures of Roſes in the Spring ſeaſon, as the Lillies by the riuers of waters, as a veſſell full of maſſie golde, emboſſed and fretted round about with pretious ſtones, and as the fatte taken from the peace offerings. What if there be a ſpotte or twoo in the white garment of the Church, a more in the eie of it? Haue wee ſuch ſtreight throates as wee can not ſwallow vp a Gnatte? What Pomegranate ſhall you find, in the which there is not a corrupt kernell or two in it? What body is cleane without blemiſh or wrinkle? what day ſhineth ſo cleere ouer our heades, as a cloude is not to be ſeene in the skie? The poynts we differ in are not worth the ſpeaking, and they come not neere the vvoorth of the good things we enioy, vvhich o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdomes want. The bodie of the Church vvaxeth by degrees as the naturall bodie of a man, which hath not his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turitie and full growth at the firſt. In Reformation it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that nothing ſhould be wanting. Princes and Povvers that be neuer ſo well affected, can not haue vvhat they vvill, and vvhen they will effected, but are compelled to ſtay opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie, or to leaue it to others. <hi>Dauid</hi> had a minde that Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhoulde bee doone vppon the perſon of Duke <hi>Ioah,</hi> for his cruell hand, and vppon <hi>Shemei</hi> for his ſpightfull tongue: yet his meanes ſerued him not ſo vvell, inſomuch that he was driuen to committe the care theereof vnto <hi>Salomon</hi> after him. And truly <hi>Antimachus,</hi> if ſuch a forme of gouernement in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> tooke place, which you and your fraternitie would giue vs, doe you thinke that the Church would bee then at quiet, and not as much diuided as it is now? When we haue laboured all we may, Sathan will ſow and ſtrow his vnhappie cockle of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in the furrowes of the Lords field: what factions were
<pb facs="tcp:177636:25"/>in the Church in the times of the Apoſtles, when ſome ſaide they were of <hi>Paul,</hi> others of <hi>Cephas,</hi> others of <hi>Apollo. Paul</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from <hi>Peter</hi> and reprooued him. And <hi>Barnabas</hi> in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie diſpleaſure, departed from <hi>Paul. Theophilus, Epiphanius, Chryſoſtome, Augustine, Ruffinus, Hierome,</hi> nouriſhed implacable contentions together. The Eaſt Church was diuided from the Weſt, about Leauen, and Eaſter: in all counſels continually new Creeds &amp; Decrees were coyned. Of late, yet the two names of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Zwinglius,</hi> haue made no ſmall garboiles in the Church. And the Papiſts would choake vs with this bone of our home-borne new-fangleneſſe and factions. But therein they pull themſelues by the noſes: for I know no greater wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glers then themſelues. For their Scotiſts and Thomiſtes, are together by the eares about the dunſicall diſtinction of Merits, of Congruitie, and Condignitie; about originall ſinne in the Virgine Mary; about ſolemne and ſimple vowe. The Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts contend for auricular confeſſion, concluding it to bee, <hi>Deiure humana &amp; poſitiua:</hi> that it is of humane and poſitive conſtitution: And the Schoole men ſquabble with them for it, and auouch, that it is <hi>Deiure diuino:</hi> it hath foundation in diuine ordination. <hi>Albertui Pigghius</hi> differ from <hi>Caietan, Thomas</hi> from <hi>Lambard, Scotus</hi> from <hi>Thomas, Oceanus</hi> from <hi>Scotus, Allienſis</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>m <hi>Occan,</hi> the <hi>Nominalls</hi> from the <hi>Realists.</hi> How many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entions haue there beene among the Monkes and ſhauelings, which ſome in fiſh, ſome in fleſh, ſome in hearbes, ſome in ſhooes, ſome in ſlippers, ſome in a linnen garment, ſome in a woollen weede, haue repoſed religion, while ſome would goe in blacke, other in white; others would be more broadly, others more narrowly rounded and ſhauen, others would be in their ſlippers, and others go bare-foote; others would be girt, others would be looſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antim.</speaker>
                  <p>What of all this? be the peoples mindes neuer ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, we cannot be too religious: we muſt therefore come as nie perfection as we can, according to Chriſts precept; <hi>Be yee perfect, as your heauenly Father is perfect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>True, but this your conformitie nothing derogateth
<pb facs="tcp:177636:26"/>from this your Chriſtian perfection or profeſſion: but it will rather giue furtherance vnto it. For it is a rule in Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie and reaſon, <hi>Vis vnita fortior:</hi> conioyned helpe is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antim.</speaker>
                  <p>But how doe wee goe forward in this perfection, when we keepe at a ſtay, as the Sunne in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> or the Moone in the valley of <hi>Aiaton,</hi> in the daies of <hi>Ioſua?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>This ſtay is in yourſelfe, or rather your backwardnes, that ſtop the courſe of your good proceedings in the ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of your affections. The regions are not onely white vnto harueſt, but drie to the fire: therefore we cannot labour too much in the Lordes harueſt: now you put your ſelfe to ſilence for theſe ceremonies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antim.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe ceremonies came in with the childhoode of the Church, in the minoritie of it, and the grace of them is gone now with the times:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>When I was a childe</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>I did as a childe: but ſince I was a man, I did put away childiſhneſſe.</hi> And now ſeeing we know God, or rather are knowne of God, why turne ye then to the impotent and beggerly ceremonies of the law?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>The godly fathers of the Church, in the pureſt eſtate thereof, commended them vnto vs; and antiquitie, a teſtimonie not to be reprehended, hath confirmed them, and euer there was good vſe of them, and neuer any harme in them. <hi>Irenaus</hi> the antient father, often appealed to thoſe antient Churches that were nigheſt Chriſts times; Antiquitie is the ſeale of the grace of the ceremonies, as it is of ſundry other things: wine that is the oldeſt, is beſt: for no man that may haue olde wine, will taſte of new; for he ſaith, that old is better. It graceth wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which is rather in the older then the younger ſort: wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons are for young men,<note place="margin">Prou. 22.</note> and wiſedome for the old. It adorneth the truth, for that is trueſt, which is firſt: and cuſtome that is oldeſt, is beſt approoued. Wherefore it is prouided by law, not to remooue the antient borders which our fathers haue placed. And friendſhip that hath beene of longeſt continuance, is of beſt countenance.<note place="margin">Eccli 9.</note> Wherefore it is ſaid; <hi>Forſake not thine owne
<pb facs="tcp:177636:26"/>friend, and the friend of thy father: for a new friend will not be like him.</hi> Olde trained and practiſed ſouldiers are more skilfull and coragious. Wherefore <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ytus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Alexander; Dooſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe thy father</hi> Philips <hi>Souldiers?</hi> The landes and poſſeſſions that haue beene longeſt in the name and in the ſtocke, is of chiefeſt reckoning. Which reſpect was ſo great with <hi>Nabaoth,</hi> as no money that the King could offer him, could preuaile for the purchaſing of it: but he ſhooke him off with this abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute deniall,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>God keepe me from ſelling the inheritance of my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors to them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> And this was <hi>Barzalia,</hi> his plea to <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he would haue induced him to liue in the Court with him: <hi>I am foureſcore yeeres old; I will therefore goe into mine owne cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and I will bee buried in the graue of my father and my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antim.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceiue that you are the ceremonies great mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and heerein you are not to be miſliked, that your nature is according to your name, ſtudious of the outward peace of the Church: wherein I would concurre for peace ſake with you, but that theſe outward Rites are ſo offenſiue to my conſcience, and verie zeale draweth my inclination from them to the other ſide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt not holde forth the target of Conſcience, to defend diſorder: your conſcience and zeale muſt haue a good cauſe of its ſide, or elſe it will be wrong with you. I will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way preiudice this your zeale and conſcience, but I muſt tell you this; that the worſt ſort of all, take vp this plea and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation for themſelues,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> to ſhadow their nefarious and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doings. <hi>Abſolon,</hi> when hee went to proiect his rebellion, made pretence and colour to his father of religion; that he was to goe to performe his vowes to the Lord in <hi>Hebron.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>Saul</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended conſcience and zeale of ſacrifice and obedience, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the fatteſt cattell of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> when hee was moſt diſobedient.<note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Herod</hi> ſeemed to be zealous to worſhip the child Chriſt, when his meaning was contrary,<note place="margin">Iohn 12.</note> vtterly to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed him. <hi>Indas</hi> made as though conſcience to the poore touched him, when he murmured againſt the deuotion of the
<pb facs="tcp:177636:27"/>woman, that brake the ſweete and pretious box of ointment vpon the head of our Sauiour, whenas he cared not a farthing for the poore, but rauiſhed and robbed them, being a purſebea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and a pilferer. The old <hi>Donatiſts</hi> in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time, made a conſcience in breaking their owne neckes, as our moderne Anabaptiſts that ſprang out of them, make it a matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, of breaking the necke of the Churches gouernement. Wherein <hi>Antimachus,</hi> I doe not meane you, or any of your fellowes, God is my recorde, yet I muſt needes ſay you beare them companie a mile or twaine in the way, though there your diſcretion ſerueth you to leaue them. There is zeale in you, but yet it is ſuch, as ſomewhat beguileth you, with a copie and countenance that it hath of the truth. For as the wicked hang this maske and muffler before their eyes, when they fulfill their wicked luſts, ſo the ſimple and vnskilful are of enmiſ-led in the vain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conceit and imagination of zeale. This was the zeale that intoxicated the Iewes, of which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; <hi>They haue the zeale of God, but not in iudgement:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not according to knowledge. This knowledge like Captaine <hi>Ioas</hi> ſhould goe in and out before our zeale, and lighten the way of our zeale, and direct, as the pillar of fire that gaue light to the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the night ſeaſon. As <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> was the fore-runner of Chriſt, ſo ought knowledge to be the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of zeale, to make readie a way for zeale, as <hi>Iohn</hi> made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die the way to Chriſt. Knowledge is like the ſtarre that led the Eaſterne Wiſe-men to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 3.</note> &amp; that will leade our zeale vnto the truth. The ſpirit of zeale is ſampled to fire, yet a boll of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is to be caſt vpon it, ſomwhat to quallifie the fury of this fire. Wherefore, as Chriſt baptized with fire, ſo <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> did baptize with water. A great heate is naturally in zeale, which by letting in acoole winde and ayre,<note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> would be moderated: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as the Holy-ghoſt came downe in fire, ſo he came downe in a mightie winde, that doth much abate the heate of the fire. There is a golden meane; as in all other things, ſo in Knowledge, in Zeale,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.3. Exod. 16.18.</note> according to this ſaying of the Apoſtle; <hi>Be wiſe with ſobrietie.</hi> It was vnlawfull in the Iewes, to gather too much or
<pb facs="tcp:177636:27"/>too little Manna, wherefore their meaſure was appointed them, and they were ſtinted in the proportion of it: which hath a good application to zeale, that it neither may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound. or bee defectiue. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was willed to cry,<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.</note> and to cry ſomewhat highly; but he was not bidde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are and to rende his throate and the ayre with his voyce. Zeale, and that in ſome height, is good, but there may too much ſtrength be put to it, which will quite marre it.<note place="margin">Mar. 10.28.</note> It was zeale in the Diſciples that wrought with them, when they forſooke all to follow Chriſt, and it was good, and well eſteemed of by Chriſt. And it was zeale that kindled the coales of wrath in the breaſts of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples againſt the Samaritans,<note place="margin">Luke 9.55.</note> when they would haue plucked fire from heauen to haue conſumed them, if Chriſt would haue ſuffered them: but this was prepoſterous, inconſiderate, braine-ſicke, wherefore Chriſt controled it.<note place="margin">Iud. 4.</note> As <hi>Barak</hi> would not goe to warre without <hi>Deborah</hi> againſt <hi>Siſara,</hi> ſo let vs not warre with our zeale, without our other companion of knowledge. Zeale without knowledge, is as <hi>Sampſon</hi> without eyes, who could not take hold of the arches of the houſe: it cannot finde out the principall things: <hi>Vaeſoli:</hi> woe be to him that is alone, ſaith Wiſedome: ſo wo be to zeale alone, not accompanied with knowledge. Zeale and knowledge of God,<note place="margin">1. Kings 20.</note> are as the two Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were the ſupporters of <hi>Salomons</hi> Throne. And he that combineth them and coupleth them together, he ſhall be like <hi>Moſes</hi> in meekeneſſe, and <hi>Phineas</hi> in feruour. Wherefore, as wine is delaide by water, ſo is zeale with knowledge. As the Pinneſſe without a Pilot, is in perill of rockes, and as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die without the eye is in hazzard of falling; ſo zeale without knowledge, that is the eye of zeale and ruleth it, is in danger of miſ carrying. For it is not a bare good intention and zeale that muſt iuſtifie our good actions: but ſuch mature knowledge muſt leade vs forth to them, as we may be able to warrant them. The great variance among vs, I wot well; not for ſo great cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I feare me is not warrantable. When the Lord willed <hi>Eliah</hi> to ſtand vppon the mount before the Lord, it is ſaide,<note place="margin">1. Kings 19.</note> that a mightie ſtrong winde rent the mountaines, and brake the rockes before the Lord, but the Lord was not in the winde: and after
<pb facs="tcp:177636:28"/>the winde, came an earth-quake, but the Lord was not in the earth-quake: and after the earth-qake came fire, but the Lord was not in the fire: and after the fire, came a ſtill and ſoft voice, and there the Lord vvas. In the ſtormie vvindes and tempeſts of the Church, that offer to ſhake it in the verie foundation, in the earth-quake and fire of our endleſſe contentions, the Lord is not; but he is in the ſtill voyce that ſeeketh and enſueth the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antun.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue nothing elſe to ſay in the cauſe, but I promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call for your counſell: and therefore if you pleaſe, addreſſe your ſelfe to that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>My counſell ſhall be: firſt, That you weigh the points in controuerſie betweene vs, in equall ballances, and that you ſtriue not by inuention of argument, to hang lumpes of lead to the heeles of them, to make them heauier then they are of themſelues, You may weigh our cauſe vneuenly on the weights two wayes: for in any of theſe two, there may be deceit in all weights. Firſt, when a thing is weighed ouer haſtily. Be not ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore too readie &amp; raſh in iudgement, in condemning ſuch things as may well in any free eſtate be tolerated. Secondly, when one part of the ballance is heauier then another; which is, when thou commeſt aggrauated with preiudicate affections againſt the ſetled ceremonies, when thou art rather led by thy wil, then reaſon. When you haue ſet theſe ceremonies vpon the tenters of your inuectiues, and grounde the face of them betweene the mill-ſtones of your fore-ſtalde affections, you ſhall neuer perſwade the wiſe, that either they are of hurtefull nature, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe contrarie to the word of God: but in ordinary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding they will be deemed to be indifferent. Secondly, you are in the next place to be aduiſed, how you wrong other Churches, by your bitter ſermons againſt theſe ceremonies, which haue alwaies hetherto entertained them as lawfull and laudable.<note place="margin">Iob 47.</note> 
                     <hi>Eliphas</hi> was very imperious ouer <hi>Iob,</hi> not conſidering himſelfe. The Iewes very notable hypocrites themſelues, and looſe liuers, ſnebbed and ſnatched vp the Gentiles at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which ſaid;<note place="margin">Iſai. 63.5</note> 
                     <hi>Stand apart, come not neere to mee, for I am belier
<pb facs="tcp:177636:28"/>then thou.</hi> We are not ignorant how farre the authoritie of the Church may extend, and wee willingly confeſſe, that it ought to rule by the Scepter of the word, and that it may not any way countermaund that that ſtandeth like Mount <hi>Syon,</hi> that may not be remooued: the whole world, the Lords building, and the heauens, the beautifull roofe thereof, muſt periſh before any tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the word muſt periſh and fall to the ground. But of this we are well aſſured, that it hath leaue and libertie to authorize ceremonies that are of mixt kinde, and that we are neither to condemne ſuch, or vnreuerently to eſteeme them. I agree with thee, that which is not of faith is ſinne:<note place="margin">Rom. 14 2</note> yet that wee may carry a quiet conſcience, and haue the teſtimoniall thereof in our actions, it maketh much that the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>All thinges are cleane to thoſe that are cleane:</hi> as that alſo which he ſaith to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Euery creature of God is good.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.4.</note> Now it is not neceſſarie, that we ſhould haue expreſſe mention of euery thing brought into vſe in the Church, in the holy Scriptures: it is enough, that by faith in generalitie we know, that indifferent things cannot pollute or defile ſuch that are of a pure minde and conſcience. Thirdly, I wold further wiſh you to giue great reſpect to eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall lawes, that tend to order, grauitie, decencie, and are not blinded with any ſuperſtition or impietie. <hi>Socrates</hi> would not weare <hi>Siconian</hi> ſhooes, though they were well made, and fit for his feete, becauſe they were not comely for his calling. But this exception taketh no place in the preſcribed habite and attire of Miniſters, it beeing as graue and ſeemely as any can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed. The very Turkes themſelues, are deuoted wholly to the cuſtome of their Countrey, in their forme of raiment, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their degrees: and ſhall not Chriſtians ſhew conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in this caſe, according to comelineſſe and ſobrietie? Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes are not to giue place to mens humours, but men muſt reſigne their humours to cuſtomes, vnleſſe they can inferre better reaſons againſt them. Much have beene attributed by the better ſort, to good and honeſt cuſtomes. <hi>Zacharias</hi> did not onely performe ſacrifices, but it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> that he did this dutie according to cuſtome.<note place="margin">Luke. 2.</note> The parents of Chriſt came yeerely to
<pb facs="tcp:177636:29"/>
                     <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to fulfill the cuſtome. Our Sauiour went to the Mount of <hi>Oliues</hi> to pray,<note place="margin">Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 26. 1 Cor. 11.</note> it being his cuſtome ſo to doe. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> citeth the cuſtome of the woman, whilſt they came together to the Church for praier ſake. Yea, bad men haue yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the cuſtomes of their times, to grant ſuch libertie, which otherwiſe of their owne accorde, without the authoritie of preſcription,<note place="margin">Matt 29. Acts 25.</note> they would not haue affoorded. <hi>Pilate</hi> was contented to haue Chriſt looſed, alleadging for it, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Iewes, which was, to diſmiſſe a priſoner yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at this feaſt of Paſſeouer. <hi>Feſtus,</hi> the Tribune of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vrgeth the cuſtome of the Romans againſt the Iewes, which intended the Apoſtles death; whereby hee eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a ſtrong and ſtrange conſpiracie proiected againſt him. The Lord is witneſſe to my ſoule, how little my meaning is, by theſe illuſtrations, to holde vp the head of abſurde cuſtomes, that aime at ſuperſtition. But mine eyes heerin are bent vppon the cuſtomes of our church, by ſuch examples as theſe, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all of the aduerſe parte to conformitie thereunto, and not ſo boldely and baldly as they doe, to abaſe our honeſt cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes. Fourthly, If I may alſo be meekely heard of you, I would put you in minde of your obedience to lawe; and hovv ridiculous and contemptible it would be to an eſtate, to repeale and change Lawes, enacted by graue and learned iudgement, at cuery ydle motion of a newfangle male content. It was the poſitiue injunction of the Locrians,<note place="margin">Demoſthenes couer. Demoer.</note> as <hi>Demosthenes</hi> beareth witneſſe, that hee that ſhould offer to put vppe a new Lawe, ſhould come with an halter aboue his necke to the Parlement, that if there were better reaſon againſt his lawe, hee ſhould be truſſed vp for it. I wiſh not the vndooing of any ones life, that hath a forge in his head for new lawes, but I wiſh him ſeuere cenſure that is too buſie with his billes, and tender vs for Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and Conſtitutions, the crochets &amp; conceits of his wooll-gathering wittes. The Epheſian <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> as <hi>Laertius</hi> dooth report, ſaieth; That Cittizens ought to fight no leſſe for their lawes than for their walles. The Graecians had their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> their Prefects and Officers, whoſe charge it was to protect
<pb facs="tcp:177636:29"/>enacted lawes, and to cenſure the delinquents.<note place="margin">Cice. pro Cluent.</note> They confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the neceſſitie, and the nature of publique lawes, the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour calling them <hi>Vincula reipublica, furdamentum libertatis, fontem aequitatis,</hi> The bonds of the common wealth, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of libertie, and the fountaine of equitie. What ſhall then become of the ſeuerall partes that are knitte together by the bandes of good lawes, and doe very well when the bondes thereof are broken? muſt not the whole ſtructure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition come downe when the foundation is vndermined? yee may not diſturbe and trouble a publique ſtreame that is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the countrey, vnder paine of a great puniſhment: but the fountaine of our welfare is diſquieted, in our immoderate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious communications. For how can a plant thriue that is often remooued? It is <hi>Senecaos</hi> propoſition, and it is true in obſeruation; <hi>Non conualeſcit planta quae ſaepiut transfertur.</hi> And this hath alluſion to the alteration of lawes by <hi>Seneca</hi> in <hi>Oedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pode; Nan expedit concutere ſoelicem ſtatum:</hi> It is not good to be buſie with a well ordered ſtate. <hi>Plato</hi> would not haue a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth to be cloyed with many lawes. Fewer lawes then we haue already, and better executed, might ſerue our turne. And commonly it is ſeene, that the older are the better. It is the <hi>Item</hi> that <hi>Tacitus</hi> giueth vs; <hi>Super ommibus negotijs melius &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctius elim prouiſum, &amp; quae connectu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ur in deterius mutari:</hi> In all matters, that which is beſt and righteſt hath beene fareſeene, and exchange happeneth to the woorſt. Wherefore <hi>Valerius</hi> would haue nothing abated of olde cuſtome, but woulde haue euery article and particle conſiſt in his former vigor; <hi>In mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis rebus omnia antiquae conſuetudinis momenta ſeruanda:</hi> In the triflingeſt things that are, all the appurtenances to antient vſe are to be retained. Of which minde was the Emperour <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus,</hi> as may appeare out of his admonition to the Senate, ſaying; <hi>Obſeruate leges quas habetis viriliter, ne mutate vllas, na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> quae manent in cedem ſtatu et ſipeiora ſunt, vtilior a ſunt quàm ea quae ſemper mutantur, et ſtapparent meliora eſſe.</hi> Obſerue roundly the lawes which ye haue already, alter them not: for thoſe that doe ſtand in the ſtate they were before, albeit they be worſer, are
<pb facs="tcp:177636:30"/>more vſefull than thoſe that are alwayes chaunged, though they ſeeme to be better.<note place="margin">Thucidides li. 6</note> With whom conſenteth <hi>Altibiades</hi> in <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidide;</hi> Holding that people to be in beſt caſe, who are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by their preſent cuſtoms and lawes, without alteration, although they be not ſo good. The Epidaurians inhibited their people to trauell into forraine parts, or to vſe traffike in ſtrange places, fearing left they ſhould bring home with them forraine and ſtrange faſhions. It is daungerous to pull downe an olde wall; but more daungerous to pull downe olde lawes. Sodaine alteration, as it is perillous to the naturall bodie, ſo it is as much hurtfull to the body politique. A change muſt come, <hi>in teſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> gradu, ſenſim ſine ſenſu,</hi> to be the better borne. Wee ſee how the dayes alter in their encreaſe and decreaſe, as the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not diſcerned, which the vncreated Wiſedome hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for the good of all creatures, which with a ſodaine great mutation would not be alittle damnified; <hi>Ars artium, dsſcsplina diſciplinarum regere hominem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory Nazianzene:</hi> It is an arte of all artes, and a diſcipline of all diſciplines to gouerne a people. <hi>Nullum animal moroſius eſt, nullum maiori arte tractan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum:</hi> No creature is more froward than man, and none is to be more politiquely handled,<note place="margin">Xenophon.</note> ſaith <hi>Seneca. Facilius regere omnes alias creaturas quàm hominem:</hi> It is caſier to rule all creatures, than man. Nowe cuſtome is an other nature with them, and they eaſily doe that which they haue done alwayes: but inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations will not be admitted without diuiſion and diſſention: wherefore prouidence and good heede is to be taken,<note place="margin">Cic. ad. Attic libr. <hi>11.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> as the Orator preſcribeth in tranſpoſing lawes; <hi>Vt quam minimo ſonitit fiat:</hi> That it may be doone with the leaſt dinne and noyſe that may be. It is recorded of <hi>Augustus,</hi> that hee compaſſed not all thinges that hee hadde plotted, at the firſt, but ſome things hee brought about preſently, the reſt hee diſpatched at his conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Antim.</speaker>
                  <p>But alittle to interrupt your counſell: May not au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie doe well to diſpenſe with vs that are contrary minded, for Conſcience ſake, and ſo holde on the forme of Lawe in vſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:177636:30"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iren.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aequalitaes prima pars aequitatis est,</hi> ſaieth <hi>Seneca,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Seneca in epiſt.</note> The firſt and chiefe parte of Equitie is Equalitie. There be many beſide you that haue but ſmall deuotion to ſome of the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, did not publique lawe commend them and commaunde them. And why ſhould they be bound, and you go free? Such a diſpenſation would but breede more enny and diuiſion. For if there were ſuch heart-burning and affections in the brethren againſt <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> about a party-coloured garment, do you thinke that there would not be oddes amongeſt vs in the difference of the garments, while the one ſide take the other to be too Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, and the other the aduerſe parte to be too peeuiſh. I doe yeelde that there may be diuerſe rites in diuerſe Churches, and that one may differ from another in gouernement. As in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> they vſually faſted euerie Sabaoth day, but in <hi>Millaine</hi> they did not.<note place="margin">Aug. epist. <hi>118.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Policarpus</hi> and <hi>Anicetus</hi> kept the peace between themſelues, though the one woulde not yeelde to the other in ceremonies, but each of them peremptorily maintained their owne cuſtomes, but they were of ſeuerall Churches. But my ſimple diſcretion can not ſee how it may ſtand with any conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie, thar wee ſhould haue a confected and compound e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Church, that it ſhould be as <hi>Bifrons Ianus,</hi> beare two faces in one hoode, and how ſuch conniuencie and tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be any way tolerable. It is the plea of the naturall mother before <hi>Salomons</hi> Tribunall, That the childe ſhould be in no wiſe diuided, as the wrong mother woulde haue it, but that ſhee might haue all, or none at all. I am the mouth of my brethren to our ſoueraigne <hi>Salomon,</hi> that without partialitie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one might be vnder lawe indifferently; that as wee all of vs ſerue one Maiſter, ſo that we may all of vs weare the like li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie; whether it be white or blacke, we are indifferent, as it pleaſeth thoſe that are at the ſterne of gouernement, whoſe wiſedome wee knowe, and whoſe trueth wee doe not ſuſpect. This was the cauſe that the Roman Empire continued ſo long, and that in ſuch proſperitie, becauſe the ſalte of Lavve ſeaſoned all alike. For as <hi>Epaminondas</hi> ſaith, Then is peace eſtabliſhed, vvhen equalitie is preſerued;<note place="margin">Cic. in. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>Morum ſimilitudo coniungit ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiam:</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177636:31"/>It is ſimilitude of manners that ioyne friends together; Wherefore <hi>Ius</hi> is called by the Orator <hi>Par:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er diuinat. libr. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> And this equalitie (as ſaieth <hi>Euripides</hi>) is the lavve of mankinde. And this is my deciſion and determination of your latter queſtion. 5. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I conclude my counſell with my louing exhortation vnto you, to entertaine theſe tolerable conditions, for the peace ſake of the Church, vvhich we ought to put on as our own bowels, vvhich is the ſweete direction of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> I knovv not in how many places,<note place="margin">1. Corint. 1.10</note> as vvhen hee ſaieth; <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that yee all ſpeake one thing, and that there be no diſſenſions among you: But be yee knit together in one minde and in one iudgement.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 15.5.</note> Againe, <hi>The God of patience and conſolations giue you that yee be like minded one towardes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to Chriſt Ieſus; That yee with one mind, and with one mouth may praiſe God, euen the Father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Corint 13.</note> Againe, <hi>Liue in loue and peace, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi> Againe, <hi>Let your conuerſation be as it becommeth the Gospel of Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philip. 1.27.</note> 
                     <hi>that whether I come and ſee you, or elſe be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I may heare of your matters, that yee continue in one ſpirite, and in one minde, fighting together through the faith of the Gospell.</hi> Vnitie is the verie body of Diuinitie, and the very ſcope and end of Chriſtianitie, vvhich vvhoſo ſhall diſſolue, bringeth all things out of courſe. For, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> diſputeth it,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> We are all of vs but one joynt body vnder one head Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: one and the ſelfeſame ſpirite quickeneth this body; there is but one hope of our vocation, one Lorde, one faith, one bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, one God and Father of all, vvhich is aboue all, through all, and in all. It is all that Chriſt prayeth for to his Father for vs,<note place="margin">Iohn 17.</note> when hee went to ſuffer; <hi>Holy Father, keepe them through thy name, whome thou haſt giuen mee, that they may be one as wee are one.</hi> And that no man ſhould reſtraine this his prayer to the Diſciples onely, hee ſaieth immediately after; <hi>I pray not for them onely, but for thoſe alſo that ſhall beleeue; that they may be one, as thou O Father in mee, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in vs.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 11.</note> For this cauſe was his ſuffering, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> profeſſeth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; That the Sonne of God was not to die for the nation of the
<pb facs="tcp:177636:31"/>Iewes onely, but to gather together in one, the children of God that were ſcattered. This was the legacie that our deere Sauiour be queathed at his death to vs:<note place="margin">Iohn 14.</note> 
                     <hi>My peace doe I giue you, my peace doe I leaue you.</hi> If a Prince being to take a farre iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſhall leaue a jewell to his wife at the time of his departure, as a ſigne of his loue towards her, and ſhee ſhould deſpiſe it when he is gone; were ſhe not to be charged with huge ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude? But ſuch is our vile nature towards our deereſt Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome Chriſt Ieſus, when wee ſo baſely eſteeme of his gift that he left with his wife the Church, when he tooke his leaue of her. Euery Armie hath his proper flagge and banner by which it may be knowne; and euery noble Houſe is knowne by the antient armes and ſcutchian thereof. Sheepeheards vſe to ſtrike their ſheepe with a red marke on the ſides, where by they might be the better knowne: the armie, familie, ſheepe of Chriſts are diſtinguiſhed by the banner, cogniſance and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke of loue, according to that which Chriſt ſaith; <hi>By this it ſhall be knowne, that ye are my Diſciples, if ye haue loue one towards another.</hi> The peace that we haue with our ſelues, is our cheefeſt outward comfort amidſt the miſeries of this mortall life, and is as the meale that the man of God did caſt into the pot, which tooke away the deathfull bitterneſſe of the <hi>Colliquintida</hi> or hear be that was in the pot. The ſicke man, though he change neuer ſo often his chamber and bed, hath neuer the more reſt, becauſe he beareth his infirmitie about him: ſo we ſhall neuer be at peace with our ſelues, though lawes were changed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our luſts, bearing about vs ſuch humorous affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. More dammages is imported both to Church and ciuill ſtate, by domeſticall diſſention, then by forraigne perſecution, yea, more then any man poſſibly can diuine. It hath bin an old and vnqueſtionable obſeruation; <hi>Concordia paruae res creſcunt. Diſcordia maximae dilabuntur:</hi> by concorde,<note place="margin">Saluſtius.</note> ſmall things attaine to a great growth; and by diſcorde, the great things of all are diſſolued. <hi>Concordia fulciuntur opes etiam exiguae.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plautus.</note> 
                     <hi>A poore eſtate is eaſily ſupported and borne vp by concorde.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cuidius.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <q>
                  <p>Et quae non poſſunt ſingula, multa inuant</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177636:32"/>
                  <p>Et quae non laedunt ſingula multa nocent.</p>
               </q>
               <p>If the confuſion of languages confounded the ſtately and magnificall building of the Tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> how ſhall not the diſtraction and confuſion of mindes, make a ſpoile of all things? To the generation and production of things naturall, there muſt neceſſarily bee a combination of the elements, laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part their contrarie qualitie, and agreeing among themſelues, that by their vnited force and vertue, gold, pretious ſtones, and other kindes of mettalls might be bred. By the ioynt aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the foure humours, the health of man is continued: and when ſtrife and debate is betweene them, all manner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies and diſeaſes are engendered, and death it ſelfe followeth it. The melodious and tuneable muſicke, conſiſteth in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and harmony of the voyce.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> The firſt world was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with water: but in contention of life it was firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, which was betweene the ſonnes of <hi>Seth</hi> and <hi>Cham.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> The <hi>Egyptians</hi> periſhed by water, but they firſt did breake with the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and were at deadly fewd with them. The <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> were ledde by the <hi>Babylonians</hi> into bondage,<note place="margin">2. Kings 15.</note> but firſt ten Tribes were ſundred from the other two, <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</hi> The contention betweene <hi>Haimo</hi> and <hi>Hanibal</hi> Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginians, was the ouer-throw of that Cittie. The quarrell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> and <hi>Athenians,</hi> that were the two great lights in the Firmament of <hi>Greece,</hi> made hauocke and waſte of the whole Prouince. The diuiſion that aroſe among the <hi>Numantians,</hi> was the cauſe they were ſubdued by <hi>Scipio:</hi> who being asked by the Gouernour <hi>Tyretius,</hi> how it came to paſſe, that being hetherto a people inuincible, they were now o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome? they anſwered, that their concord ſaued them, &amp; their diſcord ſpoiled them. The <hi>Romans</hi> felt the ſmart of this, while <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> &amp; <hi>Antony</hi> were diuided. It was a plague to all <hi>Italy,</hi> the diſquiet that was betweene <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey, Scylla</hi> &amp; <hi>Marius.</hi> But contention in the Church is a monſtrous and miſchieuous Hydra as euer was bred; and that examples ſhew. There grew ſuch hote ſtrife betweene the <hi>Orthodoxall</hi> fathers and the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> in the Syrmita Synod, about the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:177636:32"/>as kindled ſuch coales as fired all the Church: of which, <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi> ſaith thus; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, while they buſied their braines about theſe wordes they miſerably diſtracted the Church of God. The conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Church, betweene <hi>Enſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great, was great and greeuous. The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorting vs to thoſe things that make to peace, ſheweth the important neceſſitie thereof, by implying the ineuitable inexplicable miſchiefe in the caſe, by our recuſancie that muſt come vpon vs: <hi>If ye bite one another, ye ſhall be conſumed one of another.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5. Pſal. 46.</note> It is the conſequent the royall Prophet maketh: <hi>The nations raged and the Kingdomes are mooued.</hi> This maxime and principle in Philoſophie; <hi>Vis vnita fortior: Vnited helpe is ſureſt, is by common experience approoued.</hi> For two oxen will beare a greater burthen then one. Eſpeciall care is had in the warres, that the Souldiers keepe their ranckes and ſcatter not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for ſo they ſhould be a prey to the enemie. Much more is it meete for the Church to haue ſuch heedefull prouiſion, that the Miniſters thereof may keepe their ſtanding, as forme of law requireth, that they be not exorbitant, and ſallie out of the claſſes of their due obedience that they owe to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and diſcipline of the Church, that ſo ſuch aduantage might not be giuen to the common aduerſary. How came it to paſſe, that the Preachers of the Primitiue Church were ſuch ſtrong Giants, as they ſubdued the whole world?<note place="margin">Acts 4. Cant. 6.</note> The text telleth vs, <hi>The multitude of them that did beleeue, were of one heart, and of one ſoule.</hi> The Lord in the Canticles giuing high commendations to his Church, hee extolleth them for their order and conformitie. <hi>Thou art comely as</hi> Ieruſalem, <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible as an armie of banners.</hi> But what ſhould be the ground and cauſe of this maladie and infirmitie in the Church, that wee may know how to remedie it? The cauſe is double. The firſt is pride, ſelfe-loue, ſingularitie of the minde, euery one being wedded to his will, as to his wife, checking all contrarie reaſon without cauſe, and baſely eſteeming euerie ones opinion, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their owne. Euery ones owne fancie, is as it were a
<pb facs="tcp:177636:33"/>Crow which iobbeth at his eyes which feedeth it, and ſtriketh him blinde; and that which is worſt of all, maketh him in that caſe as he cannot ſee his blindeneſſe and perdition. This Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome teacheth vs;<note place="margin">Prou. 28.25. 1. Kings 16.9, 10, 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>He that is of a prowde heart, ſtirreth vp ſtrife. Zimri,</hi> through pride grew contentious, and ſo ſeditious. For being Captaine of halfe his Charets, bee conſpired againſt the King, and ſlew him, and raigned in his ſteede. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Corint. 3.3.</note> a practiſed Phiſitian, caſting our water, findeth this to be the cauſe of this diſeaſe, ſaying; <hi>Whereas there is among you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying, and ſtrife, and diuiſions, are ye not carnall?</hi> Wherefore, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this beaſtly affection of ſelfe-loue, as thou wouldeſt thy beaſt: for if thou beeſt to ride on an vnrulie beaſt, thou haſt ſpurres at thine heeles, and a bridle in thine hand. If hee bee too forwarde and would caſt thee, thou haſt a bridle to checke him and hold him in: if he be dull and will not goe, thou haſt ſpurres to put to his flankes: ſo controle thy too extraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant affections, and keep them in as it were with bit and bridle, that they get not the vpper hand of thee, and let better reaſon and ſuggeſtion ſpurre and ſtirre thy dulneſſe, that thou maieſt go on forward in the right way of thy Chriſtian calling. In any wiſe take Wiſedomes counſel with thee,<note place="margin">Eccleſ 18. Pſal. 72.</note> which ſaith; <hi>Doe not after thine owne luſtes:</hi> But ſay and pray with <hi>Dauid; Leade mee in the path of thy commaundements, for rude am I, and ignorant, and as a beaſt before thee.</hi> Secondly, an other cauſe is, becauſe peace is a jewell of that rareneſſe and price, that the world can not giue it; wherefore it is iuſtice when one robbeth an other, hee ſhould looſe that is his owne: God taketh away the peace that is ours, becauſe we take away the honour that is his, and ſerue him no better. There be ſixe things which the Lorde dooth hate,<note place="margin">Prou 6.16.</note> yea his ſoule abhorreth ſeauen, the ſeauenth thing is, one that raiſeth vp contentions among brethren. My bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thinke of this, and flee from it as from the face of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. It is daungerous to play by the hole of this Aſpe, and to nouriſh in thy boſome this lions whelpe, to thine owne decay. The defect of righteouſneſſe is the effect of diſcorde: for men embrace peace for righteouſneſſe ſake; and by their vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:177636:33"/>courſes they are diuided. Wherefore the Kingly Prophet maketh righteouſneſſe and peace to goe hand in hand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> two twinnes in this piece of Antheme and Ode; <hi>Righteouſneſſe and peace haue kiſſed each other.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 85.</note> As in a well ordered clocke, the wheeles and inward implements are ſo framed, as they walke their circuites, circles and ſtations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and they all concurre in motion, and reſt together, ſo that albeit there be very many peeces, yet in courſe and concord are all one: So in a Chriſtian Church and common-wealth there ſhould be ſuch ſympathie of affections, as, though the parties be many, they ſhoulde ſo ſute and anſwer one an other in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie of minde, as if they were conſolidated and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adunated into one body and minde, in preſeruing the vnitie of the ſpirite, in the bond of peace,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. Rom. 14.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> in the faithfull apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Apoſtles counſaile. For the kingdome of God is not meate nor drinke, but righteouſneſſe and peace. As the ſpirite dooth not giue life to the members, vnleſſe they be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together: ſo the Spirite of God quickeneth not the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, vnleſſe they be vnited and bound faſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the bond of peace. When <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple was in building, there was not within the Temple, ſo much as the noyſe of an hammer heard;<note place="margin">Prou. 24.27.</note> the timber and ſtone were broken and hewed without; which aunſwereth the precept deliuered by <hi>Salomon, Prepare thy woorke without, and make ready thy things in the field, and after builde thine houſe.</hi> It is the burthen of our Miniſterie, to builde a temple to the Lorde God of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> by bringing a people to God, whome the Apoſtle calleth liuely ſtones, to be ioyned to the corner ſtone Chriſt Ieſus: Wherefore let vs handle our hammers without, and ſtrike the enemies of the Goſpel, and not lift vp hand one againſt an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I winde vp this warning with the paſſionate ſpeech of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to <hi>Hierome,</hi> in the controuerſie betweene him and <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> which was then the argument of euery ones mouth, the by-word of the people, and the great diſturbance of the peace of the Church; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t moncor, vt doleo, vt timeo, prociderem ad pedes vestros flerem quantum valerem, rogarem quantum ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,
<pb facs="tcp:177636:34"/>nunc vnumquemque pro ſeipſo, nunc vtrumque pro altere, &amp; pro alijs &amp; maxime infirmis pro quibus Christus mortuus est, qui vos tanquam in theatro vitae huius, cum magno ſui periculo ſpectant, ne de vobis ea conſcribendo ſpargatis, quae qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>doque concordantes delere non poteritis, qui nunc concordare nolitis:</hi> And I ſpeake to you, and to your learned zealous brethren in like maner: How am I mooued, how grieue I, and feare? If I were with you, I ſhould fall before your feete, ſo much as I loued you, I ſhould intreate you, I ſhould weepe my vttermoſt, I ſhould beſeech each one for himſelfe, and both for each other, and for others, eſpecially for thoſe for whome Chriſt died, who beholde you as it were in the ſtage of this life to their great danger, that you would not ſcatter thoſe things in your Sermons and Writings of your ſelues, which you can not reuerſe when you may be made friendes, who will not now be made friendes. Sixtly, let my laſt words be as the latter raine that may giue fatneſſe to the cloddes by the influence of the cloudes, that you putte not off your calling, the Lorde hauing made you ſo able a Miniſter of the new Teſtament, in the conceit that you haue taken againſt lawful diſcipline, maturitie of Iudgement ſcanning and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it. You ſhall not onely thereby corrupt the occaſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you by God of dooing much good by your godly labours, but you ſhal be <hi>cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> of much hurtful conſequence, while perhappes ſome Idoll Shepheard may ſucceede in your roome, that will not onely, not grudge at theſe orders, but wil make no conſcience of diſcharging his duetie in preaching vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. If your owne conſcience doe not accuſe you in this courſe, I ſhall not accuſe you; goe in peace. But be it farre from me, to make ſo little account of my function, as to caſt it vp for ſo ſlender occaſion. If the difference were in matters of faith, then you ſhould doe well to contend with your vttermoſt ſides, and not to giue place to damnable doctrine, though it ſhould coſt liuing and life too.<note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> It is the exhortation of bleſſed <hi>Iude,</hi> that we ſhould contend for the maintenance of the faith, which was once giuen vnto the Saintes. So did <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt the idolatrous <hi>Amalekites, Ioſua</hi> againſt the <hi>Canaanites, Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177636:34"/>againſt the <hi>Philistines, Dauid</hi> againſt the <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, Aſa, Ezechias, Ioſias</hi> againſt the Idole-mongers rounde about. <hi>Paul</hi> had verie quicke and ſharpe contention againſt the Iewes, in the fundamentall and maine poynt of out Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by faith, and againſt the ſect and ſchoole of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, in the cauſe of the trueth of religion: againſt idolatrous Gentiles and falſe brethren, who craftily crept in, to ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Chriſtians libertie. If the Prince ſhall make lawes for Poperie, and commaund vs to worſhip an Image, wee wilſay with <hi>Daniels</hi> godly conſorts;<note place="margin">Dan. 3. Exod. 32. Pſal. 16.2. Mac. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>O King, we will not worſhip the Image that thou haſt ſet vp:</hi> Wee may not with <hi>Moſes</hi> indure a calfe in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or with <hi>Dauid</hi> the offences of blood, or with <hi>Eleazar</hi> the eating of ſwines fleſh, contrarie to law: and <hi>Timothie</hi> ſhall be wiſhed to take heede of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and euery good <hi>Naboth</hi> to defend his vineyard with his blood, euen the vineyard of the Lord of Hoſtes: and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> will firſt die before hee will ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render vp his Church to Arrians; there muſt abſolutely be no league betweene vs and Papiſts. But to ſtriue thus <hi>de lana ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prina, &amp; nodos in ſcirpo quaerere:</hi> to ſeeke out knottes in ruſhes, ſo to ranſake and perſecute the booke of Common prayer, as <hi>Laban</hi> did <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſtuffe, with the ſharpeſt edge and curioſitie of witte, or wittes curioſitie; if you take ſuch felicitie, <hi>Nobis non licet eſſe tam diſertis,</hi> wee haue no ſuch cuſtome, or the Church of God.<note place="margin">Matt. 2</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is nowe in as great an vproare, as it was when Chriſt was new borne. Thus haue you the abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my counſell, the totall ſumme whereof may be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to theſe wordes of the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">Philip. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer things are true, whatſoeuer things are honeſt, whatſoeuer things are iuſt, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer things are pure, whatſoeuer things pertaine to loue, whatſoeuer things are of good report, if there be any vertue, or any praiſe, thinke on theſe things, which you haue both learned &amp; receiued, thoſe things do, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi> The God of peace giue a bleſſing to theſe labours, and direct them to the praiſe of his name, the peace of the Church, and the common good,</p>
               <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:177636:35"/>
               <head>Irenaeus to all Secular parſons, wiſheth more heede in their owne vocations, and leſſe intermedling in matters of the Miniſterie.</head>
               <p>THe ſchoole of the curious that buſily prie into the affaires of others,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>10.</hi> Confeſ.</note> and are careleſſe of their owne, of whom <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> much complained in his time, is very great, and more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome at this time. But no ſorte of people vnder heauen are more in their ſore eies, and are nigher their ſtomackes, and more ſet vpon the racke of their torne-tongues, than the poore Miniſters. The very ſowter and cobler nowadayes, though his skill goeth not beyond the ſlipper and the foote, will bee ſo bold as to giue a blow to them that are his head, with the fiſt of his cluiſhnes The Cooke, though all his learning he in the Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-houſe, &amp; his whole diſcretion is in dreſſing a dinner, yet wil he be ſawcing Diuinity &amp; be too ſawcy with it: As that Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Clearke of his kitchin was, who bartrayed the Bible as hee thought good in defence of the diuinitie of the Arrians, whome the antient father <hi>Baſil</hi> thus ſnebbeth and cenſureth; <hi>Tuum eſt palmenia Caeſari praeparare, non Euangelium expouere:</hi> Cooke, it is thy office to make ſawce for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Scriptures like a Preacher. A friuolous Fidler, if hee be not harping vpon this ſtring, the Churches gouernement, as the biaſle of the worlde now goeth, is out of his element. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Tailer hath his ſhredding ſheares for the ceremonies, and hath a meaſure of his owne for the matters of the Church. The Smiths prentiſe wil not ſtand out, but liſteth to blow the coales of contention among vs. The common people will take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to put on <hi>Aarons</hi> raiment, the Rochet and habite of a Biſhop and Miniſter, and teach him what to do, and how to ſhape his ſermons to ſute their affections. Now to all of you howſoere ye be ſtiled, that are of the brotherhood of theſe buſie bodies, I wiſh more heede and attendance be giuen to your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall vocations, and not ſo to leaue your ſelues as you do, and take ſuch vagaries with the prodigall ſonne <hi>in longinquam regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177636:35"/>into ſo farre a countrey, the matter of Church gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being ſo farre and wide from your profeſſion, and not to be ſpanned and fadomed by the length and reach of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. It is the order our Sauiour Chriſt in the perſon of the Baylife calleth vs all vnto, <hi>Giue account of thy Stewardſhip.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> To make perfect the tickets and billes of our owne accounts, is the neuer finiſhed worke of our ſhort liues, though we neuer chop into others actions. Wee cannot beſtow our time better than vpon our ſelues: and neuer is it woorſe with vs at home, than when our affections are wooll-gathering, and abroade pink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and poaring into forraine affaires. When the maiſter of the houſe is at home, the ſeruants are more diligent, and folow their worke the better: Be thou at home, and with thy ſelfe, and the woorke of thy calling will be in more forwardneſſe. When a houſe is to be ſet vp, if the maiſter, woorkeman be at hand, euery vnder-labourer is more heedefull to his buſineſſe: who eaſily lay hold on the vantage of his abſence to prate, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe, and to giue vp themſelues to a ſupine negligence: It is thus with vs when the hart that is the chief commander that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the onſet, and learneth the hand to work, the tong to talke, the eie to ſee, and euery part to do her duetie and obey, is in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other commonwealth, and is a ſtranger in his owne. The man that attendeth to his owne charge, and contained himſelfe within the limites and liſtes of his owne duetie: is like to <hi>Iacob</hi> that kept at home and obtained the bleſſing of his father <hi>Izaac:</hi> but the ſtraggler, that coaſteth vp and downe, and will be a medler, is to be compared to <hi>Eſau,</hi> who while he roaued about for veniſon, loſt his fathers bleſſing.<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 9.</note> The fooles foote trudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth apace to his neighbours houſe, ſaith the Wiſeman; the meaning is, that the feete of his affections neuer ſtand ſtill, but walke and trauiſe through euery ones vocation. There is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of merchants beſide this that will deale with ſuch wayes, as not onely are not lucre, but a certaine loſſe vnto them. It is not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious, but very odious, ſo to wade vp to the chin in the needleſſe office of a ſcrutinor of others maners, and to ſift them to the courteſt braine, and in the meane while
<pb facs="tcp:177636:36"/>ouerſlip his owne in moſt remiſſe and careleſſe manner. The riuer that ouerfloweth his banckes, with his rage of inundation ſweepeth like a beeſome all the filth and ſoyle from the ſides, and maketh cleane the banckes; but in the meane while, while it licketh vp the pelfe of that place, it polluted and defileth it ſelfe with it. So whileſt thou exceedeſt thy boundes, as the ſtreame his banckes by ouer-running others doings, thou ſhalt the more clarifie and iuſtifie them, and condemne thine owne. The good husbandman ſoweth his owne ground onely:<note place="margin">Matth. 13. Iohn 21.</note> it is the diuell that ſoweth and ſtroweth his baggage of tares, and wilde weedes in anothers field. When <hi>Peter</hi> was ſo pert as hee would needes knowe what <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhould doe: Chriſt ratled him roundly with this ſhorte and ſharpe anſwere; <hi>What is that to thee?</hi> If wee in as godly diſcretion and conſcience as any that withſtand it, can willingly entertaine the tolerable outward go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Church, what hath any man to doe with vs? who art thou that iudgeſt and condemneſt vs? and who made thee a moderator ouer vs? who arte thou that iudgeſt an other mans ſeruant,<note place="margin">Iames 4.</note> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Iames, There is but one Lawe-giuer, who is able to ſaue and deſtroy: Who arte thou that iudgest and others ſeruant?</hi> (ſaieth Saint <hi>Paul?</hi>) <hi>We ſhall all ſtand before the Tribunall ſeate of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> ſaieth the ſame Apoſtle, from whence hee inferreth this ſentence of exhortation, as a iuſt coherence and conſequence.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudge not therefore before the time, vntill the Lord commeth, who ſhall lighten thoſe things that are done in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſhall reueale the ſecrets of the heartes, and then ſhall eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one haue praiſe of God.</hi> Place theſe Scriptures in one claſſie, and ſumme them together, and they giue thee cluſters of nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble concluſions; Becauſe he is an other out of thy skinne, and of a forraine bodie: ſecondly, and hath another maiſter: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and is thy brother: fourthly, and that one Lawe-giuer his maiſter hath power of life and death, and his Lawe muſt be the Iudge: fiftly, and the time of Aſſiſes and iudgement is not yet come. For theſe cauſes iudge not another. If thou beeſt a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, iudge him by law: if a priuate man, iudge him in loue; and firſt iudge thy ſelfe, leſt thou be iudged. If theſe reaſons
<pb facs="tcp:177636:36"/>may haue no rule ouer you: but your tongues muſt needes bee the ſcourge of the ceremonies, and of ſuch as performe them; taxing and traducing vs as Papiſtes, or Proctors and Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Popiſh traſh to ſuch detractors, and carowſers rather than correctors. We anſwer as <hi>Augustine</hi> againſt <hi>Petilia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> to his wrongfull defamation ſaide againſt that father in caſe of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall prauitie and maintenaunce of the aſſertions of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niches; <hi>Now ſum Manichaus, eligite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i credatis, ego ſum ex area Chriſti: ſi malus, tum palea: ſi bonus, fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>entum bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſum:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Libr. <hi>3.</hi> de Bap. contr. Donat. cap. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>non eſt autem huius curae ventilabrum lingua Petiliani:</hi> I am no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichee, chooſe whome ye will beleeue, I am of Chriſts thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing floore: if I be euill giuen, then am I chaffe, if well affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then am I good againe: howſoeuer, <hi>Petilians</hi> tongue muſt not be the ſame that muſt fift mee. Yea to ſuch hath this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Scripture application; Stand aparte, come not neere to me: <hi>For I am holier than thou.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 65.5.</note> There haue neuer ſuch bin wanting, of whome <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>Qui etiam te per ornamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ferient:</hi> that ſhall ſtrike thee by thy vertues:<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> And it is the ſame wiſe mans obſeruation: <hi>Vt quiſque eſt contemptiſſimus, ita ſolutiſſimae lingua eſt:</hi> the more the perſon is contemptible, the more is his tongue ſoluble. There is nothing eaſier than to reprooue an other, and nothing harder than to know himſelfe, as the Philoſopher <hi>Thales</hi> ſpeakes rightly; If wee haue choſen the worſt parte in the apprehenſion of the moderne gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that is no diſpenſation to you to eſtrange your ſelues from our Sermons. Our good ſayings doe appertaine to you; our euill dooings belong to vs alone: leaue vs that is ours, and in the feare of God, take you that is yours. If we heale not our owne ſores, as it becommeth vs while we cure your woundes: If our ſalte may ſeaſon you, though it looſeth his ſauour in our ſelues: If wee while wee are as a piller of fire to lighten your darkeneſſe, are darkeneſſe our ſelues: If while we frame you an Arke, ſuffer ſhippewracke our ſelues: If while wee leade you towardes <hi>Canaan</hi> the promiſed Land, wee our ſelues die by the way: If while we preach to others, wee become repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates our ſelues: If we plant a Vineyard, and eate not of the</p>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
